<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>O basanos tes aletheias, or, The touch-stone of truth wherein verity by scripture and antiquity is plainly confirmed, and errour confuted / delivered in certain sermons, preached in English by James Le Franc ...</title>
            <author>Le Franc, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L942</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11511</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12425785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12425785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50002)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 944:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>O basanos tes aletheias, or, The touch-stone of truth wherein verity by scripture and antiquity is plainly confirmed, and errour confuted / delivered in certain sermons, preached in English by James Le Franc ...</title>
                  <author>Le Franc, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 153 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Field ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>Title transliterated from Greek.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ὉΒΆΣΑΝΟΣ ΤΣ ἈΛΗΘΕΊΑΣ OR THE TOUCH-STONE OF TRUTH. WHEREIN VERITY by Scripture and Antiquity is plainly confirmed, and ERROUR confuted.</p>
                  <p>Delivered in certain SERMONS Preached in Engliſh by JAMES Le FRANC B.D. and Miniſter of the French Church in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Origen.</hi> cont. Celſ.
<bibl>lib. 1.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>Qui veritatem occultat &amp; qui mendacium prodit, uterque reus eſt, ille quia prodeſſe non vult; Iſte quia nocere deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat: <hi>Auguſt.</hi> lib. de Agon. Chriſtian.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Epheſ. 4.25.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Putting away lying, let every man ſpeak truth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Field,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity. 1662.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right Honourable and truly Noble <hi>HORATIO</hi> Lord <hi>TOWNSHEND</hi> Baron of <hi>Linn Regis,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All Proſperity and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving not long ſince undertook to vindicate the eminent and glorious Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the Errors and Superſtitions of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to blot out the falſe aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which the Enemies of the Church and Nation put upon the Liturgy and Rights which ſhe obſerves in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and ſacred Worſhip of God; I could not chooſe among the Nobility of this Countrey, a fitter Perſon then your Honour to patroniſe that Work: I know
<pb facs="tcp:61843:3"/>(though unknown to you) the rare qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and commendable vertues of your Honour; they being ſcattered abroad by your glorious fame; I am not ignorant what a Noble and Loyal Subject, the Great though Exiled Monarch of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> had in your moſt generous Perſon, when all things were in confuſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and Subjects rebellious to their King; I have often heard that the Sequeſtred Clergy found a Protection and Refuge under your eminent good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as your Anceſtours, as well as your Honourable Perſon, received with all affection ſtrangers, nay, all thoſe that were faithfull to his Majeſty our Gracious Monarch, whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, were welcome to your Honour: Your Lordſhip was not afraid to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture both life and Eſtate, to ſerve ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and incomparable a Prince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was your glory, nay, more then
<pb facs="tcp:61843:3"/>that, the glorious fame of your merits tels me, that your care was to preſerve the Church as well as the State; you did ſtrengthen the afflicted members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they might keep cloſe to their Mother; and now the chiefeſt of your Lordſhips Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes clearly appears to be the bringing of the diſcontented people of this Nation to a better underſtanding; that they may be united with thoſe that do ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely honour the King, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their mother the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> under the government of their pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and moſt reverend Biſhops; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me then (my Lord) if I have aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the boldneſs to preſent your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour with a Vindication of the Church our Mother, whom to protect was your great ambition, from the errours and ſuperſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> where I have had my Education; for as
<pb facs="tcp:61843:4"/>I am not the firſt who have adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured a Dedication to ſo Noble a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom the Authour is unknown, ſo I thought I might do this, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps without offence to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſeeing the incomparable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your moſt Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aſſures me of your kinde acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance, and makes me confident that you will not reject a ſtranger, who wiſheth you all proſperity and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and further demands that favour, to be,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord, </salute> 
                     <signed>Your Honours moſt humble Servant,
<hi>James Le Franc.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:4"/>
                  <head>A Preparatory Advertiſement to the <hi>READER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I made theſe Sermons, I had no thought to print them; not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe I am a ſtranger, and not well vers'd in the Engliſh tongue, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I did judge them not worthy to appear to the publick, ſeeing that my young capacity is but weak, and not fit to appear to the eyes of ſo ingenious and learned a Nation; but the urgent requeſt of ſome of my friends, and spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the calumny which ſome enemies of the truth caſt upon the firſt Sermon (which is in vindication of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the errours and ſuperſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome)</hi> prevailed ſo much upon me, that I could not but give them to the Preſs.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:5"/>
                  <p>Indeed having ſuch enemies that openly and ſecretly vilifie my Ministry by reaſon of that Sermon which I gave to bring the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious to union; I cannot but vindicate my ſelf from their falſe aſperſions, for I had no other intention in the Preaching of it then to take away the errours of the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; to bring them to a better underſtanding and make them leave their blinde and proud leaders, that they may come to their mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which their diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had ſpoiled and moſt ſhamefully defiled.</p>
                  <p>As for the other Sermons which I cauſed with the firſt to be printed by the requeſt of my friends; I give them to inform not the learned men, but the common people, that they may ſee the ſpiritual ſilence by which the ſons of God ceaſe from the works of the Prince of darkneſs; the reall preſence of Chriſt in the holy Sacrament againſt the Tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation of the Lutherans; the ſpiritual
<pb facs="tcp:61843:5"/>reign of our Saviour againſt the Millenaries Monarchical Kingdom; and the Celeſtial meat of God; that they may ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great myſtery of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by which their and our ſins are blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out through the precious bloud of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And if any contentious man will critically queſtion, or enviouſly quarrel at my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, be you (Courteous Reader) ſo far my Advocate as to plead in my behalf; that it is not my ambition to be expoſed publick to the world, being of a mean capacity, but to be accepted of my friends, and eſpecially as much as lay in my power to procure ſome good to the Church and Nation of <hi>England,</hi> which I am ſo much engaged to: I know that in this preſent conjuncture of time the matter treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of in the Sermons I give you is neceſſary to be known; and ſpecially the firſt, which I hope will make many confeſs their errours, that cauſed diviſions in the moſt eminent
<pb facs="tcp:61843:6"/>Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom I wiſh to ſtand for ever ſafe upon the ground and foundation of the Apoſtles, Chriſt our bleſſed Lord and Saviour,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>James Le Franc.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:6"/>
                  <head>S. <hi>Pauls Reproof,</hi> OR A Vindication of the Church of <hi>England</hi> from the Errours and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Delivered in a Sermon preached at Great S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Norwich.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1 COR. 11.18.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>I hear that there be diviſions among you.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I did conſider the hard uſages and tedious alterations of this Nation, where all things were in confuſion, the right being perverted, injuſtice erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Church perſecuted, I could not but lament ſuch a deplorable condition; but when I look upon that happy change which gives a new face unto this people, and brings all things to its order, I muſt ſincerely confeſs, that it is Gods admirable work: for brethren, you ſee that which to me and many others ſeemed impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61843:7"/>you ſee our gracious Prince ſet upon his Throne, which his Majeſty by the ſpace of many years could not approach, notwithſtanding the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and good will of his faithfull ſubjects; you ſee the glorious <hi>Charles</hi> the great Monarch of <hi>England</hi> in poſſeſſion of his own Kingdomes, and with him peace and quietneſs for the good of the perſecuted Church, that after a ſilence of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution where ſhe was not ſeen by the eyes of her afflicted Children, ſhe may enjoy the ſilence of proſperity in all godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>But that great favour of our God is not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by many of this Kingdom, who ſo envy its hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that they ſeek with their unquiet minde to ruine it; they are divided from the reſt of their brethren, when as they may be united together to the glory of the great God of heaven, the God of union, the advancing of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſalvation of their ſouls.</p>
                  <p>Perhaps there are many preſent that will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at my diſcourſe, but I will have them know, that my intention is not to pleaſe ſome, nor offend any; for it is onely to ſhew you what I with orthodox Learned men, conceive by the Scripture and Antiquity to be true; therefore I exhort you all in the Name of the Almighty God, whom you adore and fear, that you hear me with attention, humility and charity, and above all, if there be any in this Congregation that are contentious, I deſire them to hear me without partiality and prejudice,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61843:7"/>that I with the grace of our bleſſed Saviour may remove the ſpirit of contention which our grand Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> blameth in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> for in the 16, <hi>ver.</hi> ſpeaking to the contentious, he ſaith (if they would remain in that humour) if any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtome, <hi>neither the Churches of God;</hi> after which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their irregularities by which they did prophane the Lords Supper, and cauſed diviſions in the Church, ſaying, I praiſe you not that you come together, not for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but for the worſe, for when you come together in the Church <hi>(I hear that there be diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you)</hi> which laſt words I have choſen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you with, by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the bleſſed Spirit; but that you may have a clear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of them, I ſhall divide my Text into two parts, where in the firſt I ſhall ſpeak of the <hi>diviſions,</hi> and in the ſecond part I ſhall ſhew you the cauſes and ocaſions of them as you may ſee in my Text, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt part.</head>
                     <p>If oppreſſion be a monſter with many heads, ſo is diviſion which you cannot look upon without fear and horrour, in Kingdomes, Families and Churches, for you know that there is a civil or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical diviſion which ruineth all things in King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Cities, and Villages, for by that diviſion Kingdomes are deſtroyed, men ſlain, Virgins de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured, women abuſed, children corrupted, Cities
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61843:8"/>everted, Villages ruined, houſes by fire conſumed, Palaces demoliſhed, and the moſt pleaſant dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings waſted, nay, more then that Emperours and glorious Kings dethroniz'd; ſo that nothing but deſolation and ruine appears before our eyes, as you your ſelves lately have ſeen in this Kingdom; but this monſter of diviſion is not ſatisfied to ſpoil the glorious Kingdomes of the earth; it reacheth further unto private families to confound them, for there is a domeſtical diviſion which everteth all oeconomical order and government, and procre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates confuſion and diſorder in families, for in that fatal diviſion the Father is againſt the Son, the Son againſt the Father, the mother againſt the daughter, the daughter againſt the mother, the husband hates his wife, and the wife deſpiſeth her husband; nay, you ſee that monſter of diviſion go up and down in the houſe to the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of all things in families, for in that divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Parents neglect their children, with their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and ſpend all that they have by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and careleſneſs.</p>
                     <p>But me thinks, I ſee this monſter of diviſion go yet further, and by a damnable preſumption en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to enter into the Church of God to ſpoil and defile it; me thinks it prevaileth ſo far that the Church ſeems rather a chaos or confuſion then a diſtinct fabrick, and if that Eccleſiaſtical monſter be not ſtayed that it go no further, it will ſpoil and ruine the ſacred houſe of the Almighty God;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61843:8"/>which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did well know, for hearing of the Eccleſiaſtical diuiſion among the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> he writes unto them to extinguiſh it, ſaying I <hi>hear that there be diviſions among you: I hear</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, not by a ſpecial revelation (as if God ſhould have revealed him that which the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> would not have him know) but by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or rather by ſome that came from <hi>Corinth,</hi> who informed S. <hi>Paul</hi> of the diſorders of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> and ſo writing unto them ſaith, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you,</hi> as he had told them in the 2. verſe of the firſt Chapter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their contentions about <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas; it hath bean declared unto me that there are contentions among you;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But for a clear intelligence of the Eccleſiaſtical diviſion of which the Apoſtle here ſpeaks, you muſt obſerve that it is <hi>vel circa doctrinam vel cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca diſciplinam vel circa ceremonias;</hi> Either about the doctrine, or about the diſcipline, or about ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies where the Eccleſiaſtical diviſion about the doctrine, is that by which the true principles &amp; fundamental points of Religion are everted, which is ſuch a pernicious diviſion that from thence comes her peſtilent daughter hereſie; the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about diſcipline is that by which the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Juriſdiction eſtabliſhed for the correction of Chriſtian ſinners, and preſervation of the Church is deſtroyed, which is that diviſion which moſt ſhamefully brings forth licentiouſneſs; the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61843:9"/>diviſion about Ceremonies, is that by which the rights of the Church obſerved in the outward ſervice of God, are moſt irreverently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed and aboliſhed, which is a diviſion from which cometh ſchiſme, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of when he ſaith, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you;</hi> for the word of my Text in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſchiſmes, which nevertheleſs may be extended to the diviſion about doctrine and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, by which the Church is rent as well as by that of Ceremonies and much more.</p>
                     <p>Indeed all theſe diviſions were to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> for among them ſome there were who would corrupt the doctrine by their erroneous opinions, ſome among the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> did condemn the marriage, not as if it were inſtituted by a wicked God or by the devil (as <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> and <hi>Saturninus</hi> ſaid) but as a thing ſomerhing impure which was not fit for a Chriſtian, whoſe life was to be every way moſt pure, which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to write unto the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to have his judgement about it, which was, that marriage was lawfull for every man, as you may ſee in the 7. Chapter of our Epiſtle, nay, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable in all, <hi>and the bed undefiled;</hi> ſome among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> being infected with the Sadduces hereſie, denied the reſurrection of the bodies, as you may obſerve in the 15. Chapter: ſome would defile the Chriſtian doctrine with Judaicall Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, which ſome falſe Doctours would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61843:9"/>in the Church as neceſſary to ſalvation; moreover they would infect the doctrine of the Goſpel with the prophanations of the Gentiles, as it appears by the 8. and 10. Chapter; Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſcipline and government of the Church ſome there were among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> who would not have any, deſiring to live according to their own minds, that they might give themſelves to all licentiouſneſs without any reprehenſion or correction; which prevailed ſo far, that the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did bear with the whoremongers, drunkards, and contentious; which gave our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle occaſion to write the 5. and 6. Chapters of our Epiſtle to extinguiſh that monſter of licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
                     <p>As for the Ceremonies, there was diviſion in the Church; for among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſome would not ſubmit themſelves unto the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of them, as you may ſee in our Chapter; where you muſt obſerve that the diviſions of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> were not about the ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt, nor about hereſie which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verteth the doctrine; but about the manner of preaching and praying, and about the manner of receiving the holy Sacrament: Concerning the firſt, the contention was about the covering of the head, as if we ſhould now diſpute about a hat and a coife, for men and women had engaged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in that diviſion: According to the cuſtome of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as well as to that of the Church
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61843:10"/>of <hi>England</hi> the men were to be uncovered as well during the Sermon as during the prayers, and women as now they are, were to be covered, as you may ſee by the 4. and 5. <hi>verſes</hi> of our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, where we may very well take <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>propheſying</hi> actively and paſſively; actively, for thoſe that pray and preach, and paſſively for thoſe that joyn their vows and prayers with him that prayeth, as thoſe that are preſent at the hearing of him that preacheth; ſo that not onely he that did preach according to the cuſtome of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> was to be uncovered, but thoſe alſo that were preſent at the hearing of the Sermon, but ſome lovers of diviſions would not ſubmit to that cuſtome; Some men covered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the holy Aſſemblies, and ſome women were uncovered, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> hearing of, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth to inſtruct them about theſe things, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the lawfulneſs of that cuſtome, which the Church had thought fit to be obſerved by both Sexes in their publick and holy meetings from the 6. <hi>ver.</hi> to the 16. <hi>ver.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the manner of receiving the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, be it ſtanding or kneeling, the Apoſtle leaves it to the cuſtome and ordering of the Church, that ſuch things might be eſtabliſhed not by the common people, but by the Eccleſiaſtical Superiours; for theſe injunctions belong onely to them, as being <hi>ſub poteſtate ordinis,</hi> under the power of order, which is inſinuated in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61843:10"/>1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 14. at the laſt verſe; <hi>Let all things be done,</hi> (that is, by the Eccleſiaſtical Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours) <hi>decently and in order;</hi> but if theſe injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions regard the Eccleſiaſtical Superiours, know ye alſo that the Eccleſiaſtical corrections for the prophanation of the Lords Supper belong to their perſons, as it appeareth by our Text, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you,</hi> which hath rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the following verſes, where the Apoſtle condemns the profanation of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the holy Sacrament.</p>
                     <p>And indeed it was very ſit for the Apoſtle to condemn their profanation which was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their banquets of charity, which were kept in the Church before the participation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; for it came to paſs ſoon after the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of theſe banquets, that the rich men that were at the expences of them, would not tarry for the poor, and ſo the rich were drunk, and the poor hungry, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in the 21 <hi>ver.</hi> of our Chapter; the rich man came to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without reverence, being in that ſinfull and ſhamefull condition, and the poor diſcontented; for (as I have ſaid) theſe banquets were kept in the Church before the reception of the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, although ſoon after the Apoſtles time that cuſtome was changed, and theſe banquets kept after its celebration, as it appears by <hi>Tertul. Apolog.</hi> for the Chriſtians; and <hi>Chryſoſtome in moral. homil.</hi> 27. their prophanation then cauſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61843:11"/>diviſions in the Church, and diſorder among the Chriſtian <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which obligeth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to write and ſay, <hi>I hear that there be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But brethren, if all theſe things which I have mentioned were among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> give me leave to tell you without offence, that the ſame things are to be found among us who have deſiled the glorious Church of <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did the eminent Church of <hi>Corinth:</hi> it was that Eccleſiaſtical monſter of diviſion that ſpoiled it when it did appear againſt doctrine, diſcipline and Ceremonies; and it is that monſter that is yet ready to ruine that glorious Church, which as a Phoenix is newly born of her aſhes; conſider I beſeech you the diviſions which are yet entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt us, and you ſhall ſee that they regard the Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Ceremonies, for hereſie reigneth yet in <hi>England;</hi> Socinians, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Quakers and Millenaries, with others, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in great number, and with a damnable conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence endeavour to corrupt and deſile the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical doctrine, that they may inſinuate and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their errours and hereſies among the poor Chriſtian people; licentiouſneſs appeareth too much in this Kingdom; we are willing to give our ſelves to all the corruptions of the world; but we are not willing to be reproved for our ſins, we ſlatter our ſelves in our iniquities, and wickedly make uſe of the Chriſtian liberty to maintain our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61843:11"/>rebellion: as for Schiſm it is too well known in this Countrey, and I wiſh (as my duty with my affection to this Nation obligeth me) that that monſter might be hated of all, and that thoſe that have been contentious might quietly return into the Church; let them conſider that thoſe things which they trouble the Church for, touch not the ſubſtance and body of Religion, but onely the circumſtances of it, and they ſhall learn of our Apoſtle to hate diviſions; for (ſaith he) ſpeaking about theſe things to the <hi>Corinthians, if any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Churches of God;</hi> and to correct their ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularities about the holy Sacrament, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you,</hi> which ſhews the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious that ſchiſm about Ceremonies leads to prophanation about other things, and to hereſie, if it be not ſtayed; but behold, there are ſome monſters that appear unto me black and obſcure, coming from the dark priſon of the prince of the air, the God of this world, and that is pride with many other daughters of hell, which you ſhall ſee in the ſecond part of my Text.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>The ſecond Part.</head>
                     <p>As pride made diviſion between God and the Angels, that are now devils, and ambition did alienate our firſt Parents from God, ſo pride and ambition makes a diviſion between the Church and her children; for you ſhall often ſee the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Church to be ſo ambitious, that they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61843:12"/>will eſteem themſelves above their mother, and indeed there is no ſchiſmatick, much more an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick but is ambitious, and ſo the Shoolmen ſpeak when they ſay, that a Schiſmatick is one who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the fundamental points of Religion rends impudently the Church by reaſon of ſome Rights and Ceremonies which his ambition approves not of; but me thinks that the next daughter of hell is envy, which ſeems ſad by reaſon of the union which ſhe fears in this Kingdom, for envy loves nothing but diviſion, becauſe that vice and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate affection of our ſoul, will never permit us to like what is done by thoſe that we do not like, or to conſent unto theſe things which we had no hand to in their Inſtitution; for in the injunction of ſuch things we are perſwaded by that fatal paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that our advantage is hindred or diminiſhed: but behold there is another which is covered with a very black garment, where you can diſcern no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that is ignorance, which cannot inform us of the nature of thoſe things which are impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon us by our Superiours, for Ignorance makes us eſteem the circumſtances and garments of Religion to be of as high a nature as the body and ſubſtance thereof, and by that means we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree, nor receive the circumſtantial things which our Superiours impoſe upon us for the good order of the Chriſtian Church: but further give me leave to let another monſtrous daughter of hell appear with the others, that we may eſchew
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61843:12"/>the fatal effects thereof, in the knowledge of her nature, and that is obſtinacy, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to cauſe diviſion but will countenance it: for obſtinacy (as every one knows) will always have us to defend that which we once have maintained and blame that which we once have declaimed againſt although we know not any reaſon for it, and ſo the obſtinate men will remain in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and entertain diviſion.</p>
                     <p>Now if you conſider the cauſes of our diviſions without partiality, you will confeſs with me, that Pride, Envy, Ignorance, and Obſtinacy, were thoſe monſters which would not permit, as now will not yet ſuffer the fomenters of diviſion to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to thoſe things which their Superiours impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon them; for otherwiſe I do verily beleeve, that they had not embroyled this Nation with ſuch a cruel war; neither had they upon their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended occaſions ſo violently perſecuted the Church; for theſe things which many (who agree in the ſubſtance of Religion with their mother the Church) contended about, are harmleſs and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not offend moderate and prudent men, for not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the authours of the diviſion of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, I hope, will blame the moderation of the firſt Reformers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who ſeriouſly examined the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in its Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip, to reject the Errours and Hereſies of the Doctrine, the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and oppreſſion of the Diſcipline, and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61843:13"/>Superſtitions of the Worſhip; and retain that which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had from the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Primitive Church; nay, more then that, they took a way the abuſe of things indifferent in their nature, and reduced them to a lawfull uſe.</p>
                     <p>But for all that, ſome contentious, like thoſe that were in <hi>Corinth,</hi> of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks when he ſaith, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you,</hi> would not be ſatisfied, they blamed many things that could be eaſily paſſed by, as now ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their imitatours do; for the white colour of the garments of the Church of <hi>England</hi> offend their ſight, they ſay that theſe garments are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> as if in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the Clergy regular &amp; ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar did not uſe garments of ſeveral other colours as well as white; nay, more then that, thoſe that know the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as I have reaſon to know it (having lived among them, &amp; in their communion 23 or 24 years) are not ignorant that ſhe makes uſe of all ſorts of colours, ſo that if we would not uſe any of thoſe ſhe makes uſe of, we ſhould go all naked, &amp; ſo we ſhould prove very fit to be among the Adamites; but as S. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith very well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Pelagius</hi> what enmity is it againſt God if the Biſhop, Prieſt and Deacon, do go in white veſtments when they are to officiate.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, they will not admit the ſinging of the Creed nor many pious Songs, when other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants beyond the Sea, whom the contentious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61843:13"/>approve of, ſing the Lords Prayer in their temple, as the Dutch Churches and thoſe of <hi>Heſſon,</hi> or the ten Commandments, with that which we call the Song of <hi>Simeon,</hi> as our French Reformed Churches and others do; and if they tell me, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot produce any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Scripture for the ſinging of the Creed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwer, that it is not neceſſary for circumſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things, and that our Proteſtants beyond the ſea, whom the cauſers of diviſion in this Kingdom do approve of, cannot bring any paſſage of Scripture to prove the ſinging of the Lords Prayer, and the ten Commandments.</p>
                     <p>But their contentious humour goes yet further, for they will not have the people anſwer in the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Divine Service, and they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the repetitions which the Church of <hi>England</hi> makes uſe of; but</p>
                     <p>For the firſt, I ſay, that it is good according to the cuſtome of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to joyn our ſelves with the Paſtours in the Church, as you did this day, in the celebration of the Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for it is nothing elſe but a ſacred conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t in imitation of that which the ſacred Angels make uſe of in heaven in their praiſing of the Lord, as you may ſee in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. and the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not the onely Church amongſt the Reformed which makes uſe of anſwers in the celebration of the Divine Service, for the Reformed Churches of <hi>Hungaria, Tranſilvania</hi> and <hi>Lithuania,</hi> as I am
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61843:14"/>credibly informed, make uſe of ſome anſwers in their Divine Service; but I need not to pleade in that manner; for if in that the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſhould be alone among the Proteſtant Churches, I would hold it lawfull, becauſe it is not againſt Scripture but rather conformable to it; when the bleſſed ſpirits and ſacred Angels cry or anſwer one to another, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, is the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Concerning the repetitions of the Church, let me tell you that they are as ſo many productions of a ſacred and vehement affection like unto that of <hi>David, Lord, have mercy upon me, Lord, have mercy upon me;</hi> and that of the Angels, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy;</hi> indeed if the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould make uſe of her repetitions by number, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, ſo that by the repeating of ſo many times ſuch a prayer ſhe ſhould think to merit ſomething before God, as the relaxation of ſome temporal puniſhment, or to obtain the pardon of her ſins for 40. 50. or a 100. years; I would account them vain and ſuperſtitious, but it is clear that ſhe doth not do it, for all that the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth intend in her repetitions, as I conceive is to inflame our zeal and affection towards God; as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> left us an example, that we might conform our ſelves to it; repeating many times the wonderful favours of our God towards the humane kinde, and ſaying <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136. in every verſe <hi>for his mercy endureth for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:61843:14"/>
                     <p>But this is not all which the Authours of our diviſions condemn, for the ſigne of the Croſs made upon the forehead of the baptized Infants, paſſeth for a ſuperſtition and a reſt of Papiſm, as the commemoration of the principal myſteries of our redemption, obſerved at certain days of the year, with the Feſtival days of the Bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, the Apoſtles, and Martyrs; nay, more then that, they cannot endure to hear any thing about the bowing to the Name of Jeſus.</p>
                     <p>But for the ſigne of the Croſs, thoſe that have peruſed the antiquity know that it was uſed in the Chriſtian primitive Church for a ſigne of the Chriſtian profeſſion, as it appeareth by <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Cyprian,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine de verbis Domini</hi> the eighth Sermon, and that is granted by our Learned <hi>Peter du Moulin</hi> in his little Tractate of the <hi>Traditions, Chap.</hi> 25. and I will not omit our judicious <hi>Bucer,</hi> who ſaith, in his firſt Book <hi>De Regno Chriſti, cap.</hi> 12.
<q>I think that the ſigne of the Croſs is neither indecent nor unprofitable, non tam quod eſt in Eccleſia uſus antiquiſsimi, quam quod eſt admodum ſimplex &amp; praeſentis admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis crucis Chriſti; not ſo much becauſe it is of an ancient uſe in the Church, as that it is very inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and of a preſent admonition of the Croſs of Chriſt.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>I confeſs that the ſigne of the Croſs is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly uſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for they make uſe of it with their holy water for the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61843:15"/>of their venial ſins, which are not to be found in the Scripture, nor in antiquity, nor in nature; they make uſe of the ſigne of the Croſs to drive away the devil and ſcare him; they uſe it before a Croſs, becauſe it hath been cauſe (as they ſay) of great wonders, and occaſion of the converſion of S. <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> who (as ſome of them ſay) was before engaged in the ſervice of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, although it is very true, that there was never ſuch a man as they imagine him to be: nay, they make uſe of the ſigne of the Croſs before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their meat, ſome being of that perſwaſion, that their meat and drink cannot profit them without that ſigne; but the Church of <hi>England</hi> admits none of theſe Superſtitions, for ſhe onely makes uſe of the ſigne of the Croſs for a mark and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Chriſtian profeſſion as it was uſed in the Primitive Church.</p>
                     <p>And do not tell me, that it was upon occaſions which are not now to be found among us, for I will tell you, that now the occaſions are as great if not greater, being among thoſe who under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſt endeavour to ruine his Church; and if that were no ſin to do it in the Primitive Church, as I hope the contentious will confeſs, I may certainly ſay that it is none now to do it; but thoſe that condemn the ſigne of the Croſs, ſhould not at all ſpeak againſt it, for if they are perſecuted as they ſay, let them according to the cuſtom of the Church Primitive, make the ſigne of the Croſs among themſelves.</p>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:61843:15"/>
                     <p>As for the Feſtival days, or the commemoration of the principal myſteries of our Redemption, and other ſpecial favours of God which gloriouſly ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Bleſſed Virgin, the Apoſtles, and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, obſerved at certain days of the year; it is well known to ſuch as are but meanly read, that it was the cuſtome of the Chriſtian Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtatick ſeat of <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may ſee by <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Commentary upon the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> cha. 4. adding there further, that ſoon after the Apoſtles time the Hiſtories of their lives and deaths were read in the Church, and their godly examples commended to the people; and although Antiquity is not ſufficient of it ſelf to juſtifie this or that Obſervation, yet next unto the Holy Scriptures it is to be reverenced accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that of S. <hi>Auſtin, Epiſt.</hi> 118. <hi>tom.</hi> 2. <hi>poſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cras Scriptur as ea nobis ſunt obſervanda quae vel ab Apoſtolis profecta eſse per traditionem, vel ab uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalibus conſiliis deſinita eſſe judicantur; thoſe things are by us to be obſerved next unto the Holy Scriptures, which are judged to come from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles by tradition, or to have been deſined by general Councils.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Indeed we muſt acknowledge, that many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions are uſed theſe days in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for in the Feſtival dayes of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and holy Apoſtles, thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to merit before God in their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full devotions before ſuch an Altar and no other,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61843:16"/>and in ſuch a Chappel; they offer unto them Vows, preſent them their prayers, and give them an honour which is due unto God; which if theſe Saints had any knowledge of, they without doubt would implore the Divine Majeſty to puniſh their preſumption; for if they could not endure ſuch an honour upon the earth, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.14. as being onely proper to God, much leſs will they ſuffer it in heaven, being indued with a greater charity toward the God of glory, whom they muſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently adore; therefore the Church of <hi>England</hi> admits not theſe Superſtitions in her Feſtival days; ſhe doth nothing but meditate theſe days on the wonderfull graces of God, which did appear in theſe Saints, of whom ſhe celebrates the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration, and deſireth of God, that ſhe may imitate them in the holy life and pious converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they did leade upon the earth, and ſo ſhe ſaith with S. <hi>Auſtin lib. de vera relig. cap.</hi> 55. <hi>Sancti honorandi ſunt propter imitationem, ſed non adorandi propter religionem, the Saints are to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for imitation, but not worſhipped for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for although theſe days are kept holy in Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the Saints, yet they are not kept holy to the Saints but to God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the bowing at the Name of Jeſus, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that at firſt coming from the Church of <hi>Rome I</hi> thought it was ſuperſtitious, but having ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly examined the thing, I ſee that it can be done without ſuperſtition; for we owe to our bleſſed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61843:16"/>Saviour an outward and inward reverence, becauſe Chriſt hath redeemed not onely our ſouls but alſo our bodies from eternal corruption, and indeed we may obſerve that in <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. where it is ſaid, <hi>that at the Name of Jeſus every knee ſhall bow, of things in heaven, things in earth, and things under the earth;</hi> for although the Apoſtle ſpeaks imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of the glory and authority given our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, yet we muſt make it known inwardly and outwardly, by an inward and outward reverence: and the famous <hi>Zanchius</hi> acknowledgeth the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs of the bowing at the Name of Jeſus, in that verſe of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>whereas before the Name of Jeſus was bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemed by almoſt all the Jews, after his death his Divinity being manifeſted, he is adored of all men, ſo that even at the mentioning of the Name of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus they all how their knees to him: atque hinc non dubito quin profecta ſit illa antiquiſsima conſuetudo in Eccleſus, ut cum nominatur Jeſus omnes ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant caput in teſtimonium reverentiae &amp; adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> 
                        <q>and I doubt not but that from thence came that ancient cuſtom uſed in the Churches, that all ſhould uncover their heads at the naming of Jeſus, in ſigne of reverence and adoration,</q> and that is uſed not onely in the Reformed Churches of <hi>England,</hi> but alſo in thoſe of the Palatinate, as I have heard of thoſe that came from that place.</p>
                     <p>Indeed I muſt confeſs, that to do it as the Church
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61843:17"/>of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, is a thing ſuperſtitious, for they place ſome vertue in the Name of Jeſus, <hi>qua no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> conſiſting of its two ſyllables; ſo that they ſuperſtitiouſly worſhip the word it ſelf; nay, more then that, they ſay, that the Name of Jeſus, <hi>qua nomen,</hi> is greater, holier, and more reverent, then the Name of God, as <hi>Cornel. à lapide</hi> expreſſes; but the Church of <hi>England</hi> admits no ſuch thing, ſhe bows at the Name of Jeſus, to expreſs a ſigne of the reverence which ſhe owes not to the word it ſelf, but to Chriſt ſignified by the word; and there is no more ſuperſtition in that, then there is in the kneeling at theſe words, <hi>Et verbum caro fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum eſt, and the Word was made fleſh;</hi> but ſome of the Learned Proteſtant Doctours conceive no Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition at the kneeling at theſe words; for as <hi>Peter Martyr Coc. com. Claſs.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ſect.</hi> 50. ſaith, <hi>many there be who piouſly kneel and worſhip at the hearing of theſe words of the Goſpel,</hi> [and the Word was made fleſh,] <hi>and yet it muſt not be ſaid, that theſe words themſelves are worſhipped, but that which is by them ſignified;</hi> then there is no Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition at the bowing at the Name of <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I could raiſe many other Objections, which thoſe make who love diviſion, but I will not be tedious, it is enough to tell you, that that which our divided people, enemy of the Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and of all the Rights which the <hi>Church of England</hi> obſerveth, blames, is approved of by all the Proteſtants beyond the Seas as good or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61843:17"/>eſteemed as indifferent; which may be enjoyned and made neceſſary <hi>neceſsitate convenientiae</hi> by the Eccleſiaſtical Superiours; and I remember that I heard from a <hi>Polander</hi> with whom I was ſometimes at <hi>Paris,</hi> that in the Reformed Churches of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> and thoſe of little <hi>Poland,</hi> the people kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing did receive the Sacrament, and that theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants did celebrate the Feaſts of our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> mother of Chriſt, and of the Apoſtles; as in all theſe Churches and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they bury the dead with certain forms, which contain Lectures, Hymns, and Prayers, which as in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhew the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire we Chriſtians ought to have for the enjoying of the eternal felicity and glory both in body and ſoul, with thoſe that are departed this life in the faith of Jeſus Chriſt; whereof the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuperſtitiouſly prays for the dead, that they may enjoy an eternal reſt, and that their ſouls may be delivered from the flames of Putgatory, which is a place which they cannot finde in the Scripture, nor in the Writings of the Doctours of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, as it appears by ſome of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edeſt of our adverſaries, for <hi>Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> in his Writings egainſt <hi>Luther,</hi> ſays, that in the ancient Writers there is little or no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Purgatory; and <hi>Durand</hi> doth ingeniouſly confeſs, that <hi>Ambroſe, Auſtin, Hilary</hi> and <hi>Jerome</hi> do not at all ſpeak of Purgatory; as <hi>Marous</hi> as it is reported Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus</hi> declared in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61843:18"/>of <hi>Florence,</hi> that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> denied it; by that then you ſee that thoſe things which the Church of <hi>England</hi> obſerveth, are harmleſs, and have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Popery with them, which is ſo evident, that ſome of the moſt eminent Miniſters of the Reformed Churches of <hi>France,</hi> M. <hi>du Moulin,</hi> and the Learned <hi>Bochart</hi> did in the Engliſh Churches follow their cuſtomes, which they did approve of as good and lawful, as it appears by their letters to ſeveral Biſhops of <hi>England;</hi> for indeed I may ſay, if they had thought that their cuſtomes and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies had been ſinfull, they had not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if you tell me, why do not then the Churches of <hi>France</hi> and others beyond the Seas, obſerve the ſame Ceremonies, I will anſwer with the Church of <hi>England</hi> according to the 34. of her Articles, that it is not neceſſary, that ceremonies be in all places one and utterly like, for at all times ſaith the Article, they have been divers, and may be changed according to the diverſity of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, times, and mens manners; let then thoſe that will not ſubmit to the order of the Church conſider theſe things, and I am ſure that we ſhall not have occaſion to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>I hear that there be diviſions among you:</hi> Indeed brethren, not to ſubmit our ſelves to the cuſtomes of the Churches in things which are not contrary to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is a ſigne of a notable frowardneſs, and a token of an humour which abhorreth tranquillity
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61843:18"/>and concord, ſaith the Learned <hi>du Moulin,</hi> in his Book concerning traditions, <hi>chap.</hi> 24. <hi>pag.</hi> 346. for we ought to conform our ſelves to ſuch cuſtomes and ceremonies of the Church; as <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Lucinius,</hi> teaches us, ſaying, I think that I muſt tell you that the Eccleſiaſticall Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſpecially thoſe that are not contrary to faith ought to be obſerved, as we have received them from our anceſtors, and ſo ſpeaks S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to <hi>Januarius, epiſt.</hi> 118. ſaying, when I am at <hi>Rome</hi> I faſt on Saturday, but when I am at <hi>Millan,</hi> I do not faſt; ſo when you come into ſome Church keep her cuſtom, if you will not ſcandalize any nor be ſcandalized of any; and indeed it is neceſſary for Chriſtians to ſubmit to cuſtoms, not neceſſary in their natures, for if the evil be not ſo great as touching the doctrine, it may be very great as touching the manners and diſorders which from thence come forth.</p>
                     <p>But give me leave to go yet further, to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way an errour which is common in this Nation, and among the enemies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who ſay, that the Liturgy is taken from the Maſs, nay, is nothing but the Maſs in Engliſh, celebrated in the ſame manner the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, which makes a great impreſſion in the common people.</p>
                     <p>To anſwer unto that; I ſay, that (although the Church of <hi>England</hi> had taken her Liturgy out of the Maſs-book, it would not follow that the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61843:19"/>Liturgy ſhould not be good except they ſhew me, that all which is in the Maſs is falſe and erroneous, which cannot be: for if it were ſo, the Creed and the Lords Prayer, which is ſaid with the Maſs, ſhould not be good, nay, ſhould be erroneous; but let me tell you, that it is a falſe aſperſion and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, which the contentious of this Nation, put upon the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when they ſay, that it is drawn from the Maſs, for in the Maſs they ſhall not finde the manner of the confeſſion and abſolution of our ſins, as it is inſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> they ſhall not finde in the Maſs the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> or ſong of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the <hi>Benedicite,</hi> or <hi>Song of the three Children,</hi> as they are to be found in the Engliſh Liturgy; they ſhall not finde in the Maſs, many prayers that are to be found in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor the Litany which ſhe makes uſe of; they ſhall not finde in the Maſs the ten Commandments, nor the Commination or threatning made unto thoſe who perſevere in their iniquities, nor many other things, which are pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and truly ſet down in the Engliſh Liturgy; but they ſhall finde in the Maſs the ſuperſtitious invocation of creatures, of Angels, men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; the prayers for the ſouls of thoſe who (as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith, are in Purgatory, grounded upon the merits of the Saints, or on ſome bones which they call Reliques; and above all they ſhall finde in the Maſs a new ſacrifice of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61843:19"/>Jeſus Chriſt offered unto God the Father for the living and the dead; but you ſhall not finde theſe things in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for the Church of <hi>England</hi> condemneth all theſe Superſtitions and abominations in 22. and 31. of her Articles.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is not onely different from the Maſs in its matter and form, but alſo in the manner of its celebration, and uſe of it; for the Maſs is onely celebrated in the morning, and after 12 of the clock there is no Maſs private nor ſoleninal to be ſaid; in a Cathedral Roman Church 20. or 30. Maſſes are ſometimes celebrated at the ſame time in the ſeveral Chappels thereof, and one Maſs being ſaid, a Prieſt cometh in the place of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hath finiſhed his Maſs to celebrate his, having afore confeſſed ſome of his ſins to another Prieſt, and ſo ſometimes about an hundred Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will be celebrated in a morning in the ſame Cathedral: In the Maſs, the Prieſt begins with a great ſigne of the Croſs upon his forehead, his ſtomack and his ſhoulders, and then joyning his hands afore his breaſt, he ſaith, <hi>Introibo ad altare Dei,</hi> &amp;c. and after the ending of the <hi>Introite,</hi> after the <hi>Conſiteor,</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>the Virgin Mary,</hi> to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael the Archangel,</hi> to <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles Peter and Paul,</hi> and to all the Saints; the Prieſt goes up to the Altar to perform the Maſs, ſpeaking ſometime in ſecret, ſometime with a low
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61843:20"/>voice, and ſometime with a loud one, except it be a ſolemn Maſs, where the voice is higher for the moſt part, and the Prieſt that celebrates it doth many things that are not obſerved in the private Maſs, and ſpeaks to the Incenſe, and bleſſes it in that manner, ſaying, <hi>be bleſſed Incenſe through him, in whoſe honour thou ſhalt be burned,</hi> and that in Latine, as the reſt of the Maſs: ſometimes the Prieſt turneth himſelf, and ſhews his face to the people to ſay <hi>Orate fratres, Pray ye brethren,</hi> or <hi>Ite, miſſa eſt, go ye, this is the leave or diſmiſsion;</hi> at that part of the Maſs called the Offertory, the young man or childe who anſwereth to the Prieſt, and ſerves him in a private Maſs, or the ſub-dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con which ſerveth the Prieſt with a Deacon, in a ſolemn Maſs, goes up to the corner of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, where he takes two little bottles, in one of which there is wine, and the other water; he gives them to the Prieſt that came to him; who takes them to pour into the Chalice or cup wine and water; after that the Prieſt draws himſelf to the middle of the Altar right againſt an Image of Chriſt upon the Croſs, or of ſome Saint, where he makes the Signe of the Croſs with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, which he after puts upon the Altar, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers with the cloth called the Corporaſs: then the Prieſt comes again to him that ſerveth at the Maſs, to waſh his hands, ſaying, when the young man pours water upon his fingers, <hi>Lovabo manus meas inter innocentes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will waſh my hands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61843:20"/>the innocents,</hi> &amp;c. in the canon of the Maſs before the conſecration of the Hoſt, the Prieſt makes many ſignes of the Croſs, and after the conſecration many more, that the aſſaults of the devil may not prevail againſt it, as <hi>Innocent</hi> the third Pope teaches, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Myſter. Miſsae, cap.</hi> 58. towards the ending of the Maſs, the Prieſt ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es out to the young man, or other that ſerves him the empty Chalice, who pours wine into it where with the Prieſt waſheth his mouth, becauſe it is the wine of Purification; a little after he waſheth his ſingers, wipes them, and drinks that waſhing, and then kiſſing the Altar he bows and inclines his head towards the Croſs, and turning himſelf to the people, he finiſheth the Maſs, ſaying, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicat vos,</hi> &amp;c. except it be a Maſs for the dead where the Prieſt ſaith in lieu of it, <hi>Requieſcant in pace, let them reſt in peace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As for the Veſtments which they uſe in the Maſs, they are alſo different from thoſe of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> they make uſe of no Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice in the Maſs; for when the Prieſt dreſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, firſt he puts the <hi>Amice,</hi> which covers the Prieſts head in the form of a hood, after the <hi>Amice</hi> the Prieſt puts the <hi>Albe,</hi> which is like a white ſhirt, about the borders whereof there is ſome light work with green or red ſilk, upon the <hi>Albe</hi> the <hi>Girdle</hi> is put, which is white, and adorned with two toſſels of the ſame colour; the <hi>Stole</hi> comes after, which is for the moſt part very glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61843:21"/>and hangs on the right and on the left hand of the Prieſt, who after the <hi>Stole</hi> puts the <hi>Maniple</hi> in the faſhion of a napkin upon the left arm, and for the laſt Veſtment he takes the <hi>Chaſuble,</hi> which is a moſt rich Veſtment that covers all the others that are upon him except the <hi>Amice,</hi> which eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially is ſeen when a Friar celebrates the Maſs: beſides theſe Veſtments, when a Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſaith a Maſs, he hath <hi>Sandals,</hi> which they call Apoſtolick ſhoes, he hath the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal breeches, the <hi>Tunique,</hi> and the <hi>Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique;</hi> he hath alſo the Epiſcopal <hi>Gloves,</hi> the <hi>Rings</hi> and the <hi>Croſs,</hi> &amp;c. which are as many enigmatical ornaments, and of an abſtruſe intelligence, which we ſhall leave to them; by that you ſee how the Church of <hi>England</hi> differeth from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; the Liturgy from the ſervice of the Maſs, in its matter, form and manner of its celebration.</p>
                     <p>But me thinks, that I hear ſome of the factious ſay, whatſoever you ſay there is ſomething of the Maſs in the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and much of the <hi>Breviary</hi> (which is a Book different from that of the Maſs; to which I anſwer, that there is nothing of the corrupted ſervice of the Maſs; and if there be ſomething in the Liturgy which is obſerved and ſaid with the Maſs, and read in the <hi>Breviary,</hi> I ſay that in is what is good and what was obſerved in the Chriſtian Primitive Church, leaving what was not good to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and her ſuperſtitious inventions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:61843:21"/>
                     <head>Concluſion and Application.</head>
                     <p>Now let us conclude with Application, and to remove the diviſions which are now in the Land, let us be of one minde, and of one perſwaſion, that we may ſee this Kingdom flouriſh in peace and truth: for if diviſions cauſe ſuch diſorders and confuſions in States, Families, and Churches, as you your ſelves by ſad experience know, you will confeſs with me, that union cannot but bring peace, and procreate good order unto them; for union conſerveth the kingdoms of the earth, keeps families in awe, and preſerveth the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of God from ſchiſm, licentiouſneſs and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; you know that the God of heaven is a God of union, who hateth diviſion which deſtroyeth his works of nature, and that of his grace, in which appeareth an admirable and inexplicable union; for by the work of his grace our bleſſed Saviour united unto God thoſe who were divided from him by their iniquities, and by that gracious work, earth is united with heaven, and men with Angels.</p>
                     <p>Then let us all that are here preſent embrace that vertue and daughter of heaven, <hi>union,</hi> which leads us to the God of order: all the ſacred Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture preacheth nothing elſe but union, and as our Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth unto it the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſo do I exhort you all unto union, and beſeech you with him <hi>by the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame things, and that there be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61843:22"/>no diviſions among you, but that you be perfectly joyned together in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgement,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. and do not tell me, that your conſcience cannot bear with thoſe things which are impoſed upon you; for if you ſeriouſly conſider the occaſions of our fatal diviſions, you will finde them to be no ſufficient occaſions; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine without partiality, your reaſons, and I am ſure that you will not finde any ſufficient argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for your diviſion; for all that you can plead, will appear to be under ſome of thoſe monſters, pride, envy, ignorance or obſtinacy: do not ſay in your ſelves, I have ſo much ſpoken againſt theſe circumſtantial things, that I do not know how I ſhall ſubmit my ſelf again to theſe orders and injunctions; for beſides you have the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of an <hi>Auguſt</hi> Parliament, which you muſt ſubmit unto, let me tell you that ſuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations proceed from the devil, the god of this world, and the Prince of diviſion, who doth what he can to hinder the glorious union which we hope the great God of heaven, will give unto this Nation, to the glory of his great Name, and the advancing of the ſpiritual kingdom of his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Let us repent, brethren, in the conſideration of our ſins, which brought theſe diſorders in this kingdom; it is no ſhame before God, and angels, and men, but rather a commendation and glory; let men ſay what they will, but regard not what
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61843:22"/>they ſay, obey God, the King, and the Church; but let your obedience be ſincere and without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, otherwiſe you keep the diviſions in your hearts, which will break out at the firſt occaſion.</p>
                     <p>Conſider theſe things with an impartial eye, and I am ſure that you will endeavour to baniſh out of this Nation that horrible and bloudy mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of diviſion, and that for the circumſtances and the garments of Religion, you will not embroil this glorious kingdom with new wars, and ſpoil the Church of God to give way to all ſchiſmaticks and hereticks, who ariſe from the ruine of the Church: I could go yet further in the repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diſorders which are cauſed by conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious perſons, but I will not any longer treſpaſs on your patience, for I will finiſh my diſcourſe at this time, deſiring that the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, may keep your hearts and minde from ſchiſm, licentiouſneſs, and hereſie: <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:23"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:61843:23"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right Honourable and Vertuous <hi>THOMAS</hi> Lord <hi>RICHARDSON</hi> Baron of <hi>Cramond,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>All happineſs and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F Preſents ought to be worthy of thoſe to whom we preſent them; I muſt ingeniouſly confeſs, that it is in vain for me to offer your Lordſhip any thing, being deprived of that eminent capacity; and indeed perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and eminency as your Honour is, muſt not expect ſuch preſents from their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours; yet (Noble Sir) I hope you will receive that which I preſent here to your Lordſhip: I confeſs, it is ſomething preſumptuous in me to make uſe of your Name to ennoble my Sermon unto others, but I am perſwaded that
<pb facs="tcp:61843:24"/>the moſt excellent courteſie which ſhineth in your moſt noble Perſon, will excuſe a ſtranger, nay, will ſuffer me to preſent you with a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſilence, where you may ſee the fatal Eclipſe of the Church of God, under the bloody perſecutions of its enemies, with her happineſs and proſperity at the ceſſation of her afflictions, but ſpecially the great myſtery of our redemption, that procures unto angels and men a profound ſilence of admiration; for I am not ignorant that your Lordſhip takes a ſingular pleaſure at ſuch celeſtial me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations, your moſt vertuous perſon being perſwaded, that not onely the poor but the rich alſo are redeemed by the precious blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and obliged to give ſilence to all the ſinfull motions of our corrupted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and indeed your great charity towards the poor members of our bleſſed Saviour, and ſingular affection to the Clergy, is a ſufficient token of that verity, nay, an example to draw others to the imitation of the noble daughter
<pb facs="tcp:61843:24"/>of heaven, vertue, and force the moſt profane to abandon vice, that monſtrous child of hell; I could ſay much more of the ſingular vertues which nature and grace have adorned your Lordſhip with; nay, of your ſingular affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the great Monarch of <hi>England,</hi> and the Church, but that would prove needleſs, it being ſo manifeſt to all; that therefore which I ſhall ſay for the preſent, if you will grant me that liberty, is, that I am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord, </salute> 
                     <signed>Your Honours moſt humble Servant, <hi>James Le Franc.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:25"/>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:61843:25"/>
                  <head>The Churches Spiritual Silence: <hi>Delivered in a Sermon Preached at the Cathedral in</hi> Norwich.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REVEL. 8.1.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>There was ſilence in heaven about the ſpace of half an hour.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in difficult and obſcure things we do not know which way to turn our ſelves, ſo in the matter which I have now in hand, I do not know whether I ſhall ſpeak or keep ſilence; me thinks that S. <hi>John</hi> tels me, that I muſt ſtay to contemplate the great wonders that are ſeen in heaven at the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſeventh ſeal; it ſeems that I muſt keep ſilence, becauſe the ſacred Angels do not ſpeak themſelves, and dare not ſound their trumpets, leſt they ſhould hinder the great agitations of heaven, which appear in this ſilence: indeed I could ſpeak at the opening of the firſt, ſecond, third and fourth ſeals of the book, in which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, within, and on the back-ſide the great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61843:26"/>of our redemption, the conſervation of the Church, and the puniſhment of prophane and wicked men; for at the opening of theſe ſeals, there was no ſilence kept, as you may evidently ſee in the 6. Chapter; the beaſts be Angels or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, as ſome learned men will have it, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Come and ſee;</hi> I could break ſilence at the opening of the fifth ſeal, becauſe you may eaſily perceive, that there was no ſilence at the opening of it; hearing under the <hi>altar the ſouls of them that were ſlain for the Word of God,</hi> crying with a loud voice and ſaying, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud;</hi> Moreover, I could ſpeak at the opening of the ſixth ſeal, for at the opening of it <hi>a great noiſe was heard, behold, there was an earthquake,</hi> which learns us, that we muſt not keep ſilence; but at the opening of the ſeventh ſeal, I do not ſee how I may ſpeak; for at the opening of that ſeal there was ſilence: I am at a ſtand, not knowing which is beſt for me to do, whether to ſpeak or keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; but ſeeing that I came to this place to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you about that heavenly ſilence, I muſt break it, and implore the aſſiſtance not of angels, nor of men, but of our bleſſed Saviour, who hath prevailed to <hi>open the book, and looſe the ſeven ſeals thereof;</hi> for you know, that the <hi>Lion of the tribe of Judah</hi> is he that can give me leave to ſpeak in this ſilence, which S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, ſaying, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven about the ſpace of half an hour,</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61843:26"/>which are the words that I have choſen to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain you with by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit: but for a clear intelligence of them, I ſhall divide my text into two parts, where in the firſt part, I ſhall ſpeak of the ſilence which was kept in heaven in theſe words, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven;</hi> and in the ſecond part I will ſhew you the duration of it, <hi>about the ſpace of half an hour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>To know well the ſilence which S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, we muſt firſt enter into the place where it was kept, heaven, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven;</hi> but as that place is ſomething obſcure by reaſon of its ſeveral acceptions, we muſt obſerve that here by heaven is not underſtood the air, which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture calls <hi>heaven,</hi> Gen. 8.2. the place of genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many imperfect mixt bodies, ice, dew, clouds, rain, hail, blazing ſtars, and other moiſt and ſiery impreſſions, as if theſe productions ſhould ceaſe in its breaſt, or the air ſhould reſt from its agitation; neither is it underſtood by heaven the skie, that ſhining and bright heaven adorned with an inſinite number of glorious ſtars, as if there were a ceſſation of the motion of thoſe ſhining bodies; nor is it meant the ſupream or higheſt heaven, the place of habitation of the ſacred an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and bleſſed ſouls, which the Scripture calls the third heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. as if there ſhould be a ſuſpenſion of the heavenly actions of the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of that glorious palace; nor is heaven to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61843:27"/>underſtood in this place of the triumphant Church, a glorious part of the myſticall body of our dear Saviour; which ſometimes the Scripture calls heaven, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. as if theſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious natures ſhould ceaſe to render their <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs</hi> and Thankſ-givings unto the Almighty God who is ſet upon his throne of majeſty and glory.</p>
                     <p>For here we muſt underſtand by heaven the militant Church upon the earth, as it clearly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the preceding Chapter where you hear an angel cry with a loud voice to the four angels, which did repreſent the four illuſtrious kingdoms of the earth, with their Monarchs, or the devils to whom it was given to hurt the earth and the ſea, ſaying, <hi>hurt not the earth, neither the ſea, nor the trees, till we have ſealed the ſervants of our God in their foreheads;</hi> after which S. <hi>John</hi> beheld a great multitude of men who were to ſuffer martyrdom for Chriſt, and waſh their robes white in the bloud of the Lamb, nay, whom Chriſt was to lead unto the living and eternal fountains of waters; and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Church of God, admires the great myſtery of our redemption in Chriſt, for which ſhe ſuffereth: for it followeth, and when he had opened the ſeventh ſeal, there <hi>was ſilence in heaven,</hi> and indeed the Scripture calls not ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the militant Church heaven, as you may ſee, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.10. where it is ſaid, that the <hi>little horn</hi> which did repreſent the power of a Potent but wicked
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61843:27"/>King, <hi>intra &amp; extra Eccleſiam,</hi> within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church, <hi>waxed great even to the hoſt of heaven,</hi> that is, the militant Church: ſo in the <hi>Revelation</hi> 12. chapter, 4. verſe. we reade that the <hi>great red dragon the devil,</hi> with his well affected creatures, by his fraudulent allurements, <hi>drew with his tail</hi> (the antichriſt that follows the devils ſteps) <hi>the third part of the ſtars of heaven,</hi> that is, the great perſons of the militant Church, which are eminent in learning, humane wiſdom, nobility, and riches; and in my text <hi>there was ſilence in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> the militant Church; which obligeth me to tell you, that there are three conſiderations, for which the militant Church is called heaven.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, becauſe the birth of the militant Church is from heaven, for <hi>ſhe is born of God,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.1. and ſo I may ſay with S. <hi>John, I ſaw the holy city,</hi> the militant Church, <hi>coming down from God out of heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">She is ſo called, becauſe the inheritance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is an inheritance of heaven, and therefore it is called the <hi>inheritance of the Saints,</hi> Col. 1.12.</p>
                     <p n="3">The militant Church is called heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her <hi>converſation is in heaven,</hi> as the great Apoſtle tels us; <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. and ſo our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour calls often his viſible Church the kingdom of heaven, which agrees with our aſſertion of that word <hi>heaven,</hi> the militant Church, of which it is ſpoken, when S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:61843:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p>But having ſeen the place where ſilence was kept, the militant Church; let us now conſider the <hi>ſilence,</hi> and give me leave to make a reſlection upon it: <hi>Silence</hi> (brethren) which the Hebrews call <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>chereſh,</hi> and the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it in general, is nothing elſe but a ceſſation of the external and viſible actions of the ſenſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, and reaſonable creatures; and ſo the learned men call the quietneſs of the water, <hi>ſilence,</hi> when the water doth not move its moiſt ſubſtance; nay, the conjunction of the moon with the moſt bright ſun, where ſhe ſeems to be raviſhed in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of ſo glorious a Planet, is called <hi>ſilence;</hi> and the herbs and ſlowers which ceaſe from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are ſaid to be ſilent, but it is not of that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſilence which is here ſpoken of; for in this place <hi>ſilence</hi> is taken for a ſuſpenſion of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions of the intelligent creatures, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly of men, as the place where ſilence is kept, evidently ſhews, heaven the militant Church, of which they onely are members, not the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
                     <p>But you muſt know, that there are ſeveral ſorts of ſilence attributed unto them, which I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto you for the better illuſtration of the <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> which S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, there is <hi>ſilentium perſecutionis,</hi> the ſilence of perſecution.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>ſilentium pacis,</hi> the ſilence of peace and proſperity.</p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:61843:28"/>
                     <p>Thirdly, <hi>ſilentium admirationis,</hi> the ſilence of admiration.</p>
                     <p>The ſilence of the Church which is of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the ceſſation of the publick worſhip of God by reaſon of the perſecutions, which the Church ſuffereth for Chriſt under the enemies of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as it did appear in the birth of the Chriſtian Church, which was followed with a cruell ſilence; and I ſuppoſe that you have heard of the great eclipſe of the militant Church under the ten per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and ſpecially the tenth bloudy and moſt cruel perſecution under the Emperours <hi>Diocleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Maximianus, Galienus, Maxentius, Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Licinius;</hi> and how the militant Church at that time was in a profound ſilence; for you know that by the ſpace of twenty years the Church was ſuch, that ſhe could not be ſeen by the eyes of her afflicted children, nor by the pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſight of her perſecutours who boaſted to have utterly extinguiſhed the Chriſtians; at that time there was <hi>ſilence in heaven,</hi> for the Church of God was ſilent by reaſon of her perſecutions; ſhe was in her mourning apparel being under the croſs, the places of her reſuge were the deſarts, her palaces the dens of the wilde beaſts, her moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant dwellings the habitation of ſerpents and other moſt venemous creatures; her voice was not heard; and ſhe could not publickly entertain her ſelf with her ſweet and moſt amiable bridegroom, and ſay, <hi>I will riſe now and go about the city in the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61843:29"/>ſtreets, and in the broad ways, I will publickly ſeek him whom my ſoul loveth,</hi> Cant. 3.2. Now if we make reflection upon this Nation, we may truly ſay, that <hi>there was ſilence in heaven,</hi> when the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers of this Kingdom did ſit upon the Throne of our gracious Monarch <hi>Charles the Second;</hi> for at that time the Church of <hi>England</hi> was in a deep ſilence; her ſumptuous and magnificent build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, erected to offer to God our publick but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſacrifices, were demoliſhed, the mother and children perſecuted, and all her publick and holy meetings prohibited; ſo that ſhe could not with a loud voice call her afflicted children to give them any conſolation, or mollifie the ſorrows of their ſouls.</p>
                     <p>I know that ſome learned men take the ſilence of the Church, which S. <hi>John</hi> here ſpeaks of, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſenſe, by an alluſion to the Angel who was to perform the ſacred function upon the altar of incenſe, as you may ſee in the third verſe of our Chapter; for you muſt know, that when the Levitical Prieſts killed the beaſts which were to be offered in ſacrifice, <hi>there was a great noiſe heard in the temple by the roaring of the beaſts, which were tied faſt to the horns of the altar of the burnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offerings,</hi> and from thence were called <hi>victimae,</hi> victims, <hi>quia ammalia vincta ad altare immola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur,</hi> becauſe the beaſts were tied to the altar at their immolation; but when they burned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe there was ſilence in the Church, every one
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61843:29"/>did conſult in their hearts with the Almighty God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and as the pious <hi>Hannah,</hi> moved onely their lips, but did not open their mouths to cauſe any noiſe in the temple, as you may obſerve <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.10. where you reade, that <hi>the whole multitude of the people were praying without at the time of the incenſe;</hi> ſo by an alluſion to the offering of the ſacred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe where ſilence was kept, they underſtand the ſilence of perſecution, wherein the Church is in a profound ſilence by reaſon of her perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
                     <p>But leaving that opinion I paſs unto the ſilence of peace and proſperity, to tell you, that it is a ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in regard of the Church, of her perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when ſhe publickly reſteth from her cruel la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, begins to take breath, and publickly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a great and exceeding conſolation from her dear Saviour and bleſſed Lord, where in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition the Church of God remains in a profound ſilence, conſidering with her ſelf how God is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thoſe that are in affliction for his ſake, &amp; as he comforts them by his holy Spirit inwardly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though under the burthen of perſecution, ſo he delivers them from their calamities, and reſtoreth his people into a peaceable and ſweet condition both in body and ſoul, as it was done in the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, where the Church began to reſpire from her cruel perſecutions, for at that time <hi>there was ſilence in heaven,</hi> ſilence of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and peace; and ſo we may ſay, <hi>there is ſilence
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61843:30"/>in heaven,</hi> when the Church of God is in a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and quiet condition, without ſchiſms and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions.</p>
                     <p>But we muſt go further, and evidently ſee that it is of the ſilence of admiration that S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of when he ſaith, <hi>there was ſilince in heaven,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this ſilence tends to the preſent action, where angels and men are raviſhed in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of it; for it was kept at the opening of the ſeventh ſeal, as you may ſee in the beginning of the 1. <hi>ver.</hi> by the words that immediately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede my Text; and therefore you muſt obſerve, that here is queſtion of a great and ſublime my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery which was to cauſe unto the Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles a profound ſilence, in the conſideration of it; do you not ſee all the court of heaven to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the angels that are ſent for the protection of the militant Church, dare not ſound their trumpets, leſt any thing ſhould hinder the great and ſublime actings which did appear in the Church, to teach us, that we muſt keep ſilence, to contemplate with admiration what is acted in heaven? me thinks I ſee the Church in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſilence, ſhe is admiring with amazement that great myſtery, the object of her contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and let me tell you, that it is not without cauſe, ſeeing it is the matter of the great myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our redemption, which the militant Church upon the earth admireth in every age with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſilence; for at the opening of the ſeventh
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61843:30"/>ſeal, Chriſt God and man, the cauſe of this ſilence, appeareth, for the <hi>angel that came and ſtood at the altar</hi> is our bleſſed Saviour, as the beſt of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters teach us, <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject which angels and men are not us'd to behold, Chriſt the <hi>angel of the great council,</hi> and the <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of the covenant,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> tels us, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.1. Chriſt our high-Prieſt who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered a ſacrifice not of beaſts, but of himſelf upon the altar of the Croſs, and therefore at his coming into the world to aſſume our humane nature to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the divine juſtice for mens ſins, he cauſed a great admiration unto angels, and at his manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation procured in heaven, the militant Church, a profound ſilence.</p>
                     <p>But that you may have a greater ſatisfaction, I beſeech you look upon the 3. <hi>verſe</hi> of our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, and you will eaſily ſee the cauſe of this ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to be Chriſt our Redeemer, for it is ſaid in that verſe, that <hi>another angel,</hi> Chriſt our Prieſt and Mediatour, <hi>came,</hi> having aſſumed our humane nature, <hi>and ſtood at the altar,</hi> to ſhew us, that he was offered in ſacrifice for our ſins; where you muſt obſerve, that Chriſt is our <hi>Prieſt</hi> according to both his natures, our <hi>altar</hi> according to his divine nature; for as <hi>the altar ſanctified the oblation,</hi> Mat. 23.19. ſo Chriſt as God ſanctified himſelf in his humane nature, according to which humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Chriſt properly is our ſacrifice, as you may ſee in the firſt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſsians,</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:61843:31"/>22. <hi>ver.</hi> and in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1. although the principal vertue of his ſacrifice did depend on his divine nature; Moreover it is ſaid, that the <hi>angel had a golden cenſer,</hi> to teach us, that Chriſt gave God the Father a perfect and eternal ſatisfaction, that we might be delivered from the eternal ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the prince of darkneſs, which our ſins had made us ſubject to; and further it ſaith, that <hi>much incenſe was given him,</hi> to ſhew us, that the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar office of Chriſt, is to preſent God the Father the prayers of the righteous, and make them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable unto him through his interceſſion, which alone without the interceſſion of the departed Saints, is ſufficient for all thoſe that he redeemed by his precious bloud, as you may ſee in the 4. <hi>verſe,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>that the ſmoak of the incenſe which came with the prayers of the Saints, aſcended up before God out of the angels hand;</hi> all which things could not but cauſe ſilence in heaven, the militant Church, and raviſh with admiration all the intelligent creatures in the opening of ſo <hi>great a myſtery which the angels deſire to look into,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.12.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, ſeeing that the <hi>angel</hi> Chriſt, <hi>took the cenſer, and filled it with fire of the altar,</hi> as we reade in the 5. <hi>verſe, and caſt it into the earth,</hi> to prepare by that ſacred ſire the Miniſters of the holy Goſpel, to preach one Jeſus Chriſt and <hi>him crucified,</hi> as he did after his aſcenſion into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious palace of his Father, as we reade <hi>Act.</hi> 2.3.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61843:31"/>the Church could not but keep ſilence, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hearing voices, thundrings, lightnings,</hi> and <hi>earthquakes</hi> at the opening of the great and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime myſtery of our redemption, for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it ſhe could not but admire with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſilence ſuch prodigious effects, as many for certain do in this world at the hearing of this great myſtery, and I hope many in this company cannot but wonder at it, and ſay, being raviſhed in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration with S. <hi>John,</hi> at the opening of ſo great a myſtery, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven;</hi> but I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of abuſing of your patience, ſeeing that this ſilence ſhould continue but half an hour, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven about the ſpace of half an hour,</hi> which leads me to the ſecond part of my Text.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>The ſecond part.</head>
                     <p>As the intelligent creatures are limited and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; ſo is their contemplation which doth not permit them to conſider ſeveral things at once; for their underſtandings preſent them the objects one after another, according to the capacity of their natures, and indeed God alone is he who can at once comprehend all things, becauſe he alone compaſſeth about all the creatures of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, and which is moſt admirable in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which God hath of all things, is, that to know them he doth not look upon them, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for in his wiſdom he ſees the eternal models of all things, and in his will the efficient cauſe of all the events, ſo that by the knowledge
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61843:32"/>that God hath of himſelf he knoweth all things; but it is not ſo with the intelligent creatures, for they muſt alternatively and by degrees conſider ſeveral natures, whether they look upon them <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitivè,</hi> intuitively as angels; or <hi>diſcurſivè,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſively as men; or conſider them with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as both angels and men, as you may ſee in our Text; <hi>there was ſilence in heaven for the ſpace of half an hour,</hi> becauſe the ſacred attendants of the militant Church could not at once in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment perceive all thoſe wonders which we have told you were ſeen in heaven during the celeſtial ſilence, of which S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, ſaying, <hi>there was ſilence in heaven for the ſpace of half an hour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But this duration of time <hi>half an hour,</hi> hath ſome difficulty in its explication; for ſome learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men will have it to be the duration of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal peace of the Church of God under <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the Great,</hi> which ſeemed to have laſted but about the <hi>ſpace of half an hour,</hi> for ſoon after that peace hereſies and ſchiſms did ſpring up in the Church, as it did appear by the <hi>Arians,</hi> againſt whom the great <hi>Council of Nice</hi> was held, being called by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperour; <hi>Lyranus</hi> will have the <hi>ſpace of half an hour</hi> to be the duration of the perſecution of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, who impoſed ſilence unto the Church, and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her not to inſtruct her children, nor give them any conſolation grounded upon the merit of our bleſſed Saviour, which continued but a little
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61843:32"/>while, <hi>about the ſpace of half an hour,</hi> for ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he died in the wars, which he did undertake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> where this monſtrous Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate vomited out a damnable blaſphemy againſt our bleſſed Lord, whom he uſed to call <hi>Galilean,</hi> for he dying took ſome of his bloud, &amp; caſt it up in the air, and ſaid <hi>Viciſti Galilaee, viciſti;</hi> thou haſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome <hi>Galilean,</hi> thou haſt overcome at laſt: but</p>
                     <p>Leaving thoſe interpretations with many others give me leave to tell you, that by the <hi>ſpace of half an hour</hi> is underſtood all the time of the actings which S. <hi>John</hi> ſaw in heaven, the militant Church, at the opening of the ſeventh ſeal, from the 2. <hi>ver.</hi> of our Chapter to the 7. for the things which are repreſented unto that verſe, did ſeem to Saint <hi>John</hi> to have continued but a little while <hi>about the ſpace of half an hour;</hi> ſo ſhort a time that S. <hi>John</hi> was nothing weary in the contemplation of them; and indeed if you obſerve our Chapter, you will eaſily perceive a perfect ſilence kept in the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church by the ſacred members of it unto the 7. verſe, where the firſt angel by the ſounding of his trumpet did break that ſacred ſilence; for you muſt obſerve that thoſe <hi>voices, thundrings, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> and <hi>earthquakes</hi> which are mentioned in the 5. <hi>verſe,</hi> and ſeem to break our ſacred ſilence, do not at all break it; for you ſee that it was the <hi>angel</hi> Chriſt our Redeemer, and not the Church that cauſed ſuch things, and theſe <hi>thundrings, voices, lightnings</hi> and <hi>earthquakes</hi>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:61843:33"/>which follow after the caſting of <hi>the ſire into the earth,</hi> ſignifie and repreſent to us the effects of the Evangelical doctrine, of which the ſacred ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is <hi>Chriſt and him crucified.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the Evangelical doctrine tels us with a ſweet voice, that <hi>ſalvation comes into the houſe</hi> of thoſe that <hi>are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and with <hi>a thunder</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us what puniſhments attend the impenitent, and if the wicked do not repent, they will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed by the thunder of the divine juſtice; this celeſtial doctrine with <hi>lightnings</hi> declareth unto us the purity of our converſation, the holineſs of our life, and integrity of our actions, which are as ſo many lights ſhining before men to the glory of God, and ſacred aſſurance of our ſalvation; and <hi>with a kinde of earthquake</hi> the doctrine of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel reacheth unto us, becauſe it makes us trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble when we hear, that we muſt give an account of all our actions <hi>even of our idle words,</hi> Mat. 12.36. before the tribunal of the Almighty God, which things did not break the ſilence, but rather confirmed and cauſed it, for the Church could not but keep ſilence at the hearing and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all theſe ſacred and heavenly effects of the Evangelical doctrine.</p>
                     <p>So then you will eaſily perceive, that <hi>ſilence was kept</hi> in the latter end of the <hi>ſecond viſion,</hi> which appears in the 4. Chapt. (the beginning of the prophetical revelation, and endeth at the 7. <hi>verſe</hi> of our chapter, in which there was ſilence
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61843:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>during all the time of the actings, that the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding verſes repreſent unto us; which S. <hi>John</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth to have continued <hi>about the ſpace of half an hour,</hi> and not without cauſe; for theſe things are ſo agreeable unto the ſacred angels and holy members of the Church, that the continual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of them ſeems not long.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, you muſt obſerve, that S. <hi>John</hi> is very judicious, when he repreſents unto us, our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation in this life, <hi>on</hi> the great myſtery of our redemption, with a <hi>profound ſilence under the ſpace of half an hour;</hi> for he did know that the life of the militant Church upon the earth is ſhort, and paſſes almoſt as ſoon as it appeareth in this world; nay, more then that, he was not ignorant, that whileſt we live in our mortal bodies, our contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations upon that great myſtery continue not long; for ſoon after our divine meditations, even in our contemplations, the devil, the world, and our fleſh cauſe our attention to be turned from them to look upon ſome terreſtrial, vain and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible objects, by the repreſenting of ſeveral things which ſollicite us to obey that cruel maſter, run after its ambition and follow the ſinful motion of our luſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Concluſion and Application.</head>
                     <p>But let us conclude, and being here taught to admire with a profound ſilence the great myſtery of our Redemption, let us learn to look upon <hi>Chriſt the angel of the great counſel of the almighty
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61843:34"/>God,</hi> and <hi>the meſſenger of the covenant,</hi> Mal. 3.1, 6. our Mediatour who performed that incomparable work; for as himſelf ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.34. <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work,</hi> which was our redemption, and indeed as the world was erected by Chriſt, ſo it was redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him; let us conſider that in the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of our redemption, <hi>the juſt did ſuffer for the unjuſt,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth us, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. where God commendeth his love towards us, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for us; Chriſt a lamb without blemiſh, and without ſpot,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.19. Chriſt <hi>our High-Prieſt, holy, harmleſs, undefiled, ſeparate from ſinners, and higher then the heavens,</hi> Heb. 7.26. but let us ſtay here to caſt the eyes of our underſtanding on our bleſſed Redeemer, that we may ſeriouſly conſider the holineſs and integrity of his life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to imitate our Saviour, for ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 8.29. <hi>whom God did foreknow, he alſo did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate, to be conformed to the image of his Son;</hi> Let us conſider the puniſhments which Chriſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured upon the Croſs to redeem us from our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, which puniſhments were ſo great, that they drew from his ſacred mouth this complaint, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me,</hi> Matth. 27.46. Let us look upon them, that we may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſilence to our ſins, which ſpeak ſo loud in our mortal bodies, that the clamour of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends up to heaven, and draweth down upon our
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61843:34"/>heads the puniſhing thunder of the divine Juſtice.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to our ambition the firſt and greateſt of all ſins which oppoſeth Gods independency and immenſity, and fights againſt him for his crown of glory; that vice and immoderate affection of our ſouls, the inheritance of our firſt Parents, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth all men from their infancy, &amp; groweth with them to the grave, where in golden letters, upon a moſt rich Tomb, you ſee the reſt of our ambition, which ſhould teach us to avoid ſuch a monſter; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the birth of ambition is different from that of other vices; for other vices, as gluttony and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, have vices for their parents; but ambition proceeds from vertue as a baſe born child; for it was born in the higheſt heaven, when thoſe Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſpirits, now devils, were pure, and in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of integrity; then in the terreſtrial Paradiſe, for that baſtard daughter of vertue, <hi>ambition,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from heaven, and at the creation of our firſt Parents ſho did ſecretly enter into the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> where ſhe ſeduced them, when they were in their moſt pure condition: for both angels and men deſiring moſt ambitiouſly to be like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, did become the moſt odious of all the creatures: angels became devils, and men the ſlaves of the prince of darkneſs, the god of this world, as the grand Apoſtle ſpeaks, the chief of theſe apoſtate intelligences.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to our vanity, for vanity is nothing elſe but a mortal folly, and the object of it corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61843:35"/>and filthineſs, as the wiſeſt of kings teacheth us: Let us not then glory our ſelves in vain things, in corruptible riches, worldly honours and ſenſual pleaſures; let us not boaſt of our beauty, nor worſhip that fatal idol of laſciviouſneſs; for you know that the greateſt beauty of the world, is but a mortal beauty, the leaſt diſtemper ſometimes will change the faireſt face into a monſtrous vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, as <hi>Cleopatra</hi> did well know; for ſeeing that beauty decayed, ſhe did think to have found a way to render hers immortal, by cauſing her ſelf to be engraved upon a moſt rich diamond, but ſhe was miſtaken, for the diamond being corrupted and reduced into aſhes, it could not ſhew any thing of her decayed beauty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to our luſt and carnal affections; for you know that they deſtroy both body and ſoul, and pollute the image of our God, that we are endued with; let the monſter of drunkenneſs be ſilent, for it renders us like beaſts, being in that horrible ſin deprived of underſtanding and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and fit to commit any ſin againſt God at the leaſt occaſion that is preſented unto us; you know the fatal events of theſe monſtrous ſins, how ſometimes they ſolicite us to kill our fathers and mothers, ſometimes the object of our laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious pleaſures, and ſometimes our ſelves; how they induce us to go up and down to ſeek after a prey, which ſpoils and ruines our bodies and ſouls, and often conducts us to a publick place
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61843:35"/>to expire there moſt ſhamefully.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to our illegitimate ſwearings, let us not call God witneſs to our iniquities, nor bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme his holy name; know that it is not a ſmall matter to call upon the Name of our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God at any occaſion; and if he ſuffer ſo many ſwearers, it is an effect of his goodneſs, that they may repent and ceaſe to ſwear; otherwiſe know that the divine juſtice will make them feel its eternal effects of vengeance; and indeed that ſin is the ſin of thoſe that are damned, who in hell being not able to ſteal, commit fornication, or kill, ceaſe not to blaſpheme the holy Name of the Almighty God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to all our evil words, and all the motions of an ill tongue, which S. <hi>James</hi> in the third Chapter of his Epiſtle ſo ſeverely condemneth, for you know that they offend God and our Chriſt, our neighbours and our ſelves, they are unworthy of a Chriſtian, for as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29. <hi>Let no corrupt communication come</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed out of your mouth, but that which is good, to the glory of God, and ſalvation of our ſouls.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to our covetouſneſs, becauſe it pulleth down the throne of our God and erecteth another in our hearts, to the prophanation of the God of heaven whom alone we muſt adore, for covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs makes us worſhip the corruptible riches of this world, and cauſeth us to rob the poor mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bleſſed Saviour.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:61843:36"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silence</hi> to all our ſins, for they make diviſion between God and us, and deprive us of the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence of the bleſſed Spirit: you know bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that ſuch ſilence is required of thoſe that are in the militant Church of our God, where in the conſideration of the myſtery of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we learn that ſacred leſſon, that we muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from our iniquities: indeed ſuch a ſilence is our victory, and the greatneſs of our triumph; for in that ſilence of our ſins, our vices are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and our vertue ſhineth as a moſt bright ſtar; nay, more then that, that ſilence is a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph which excels that of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, when he made his entrance into the noble and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous city of <hi>Babylon,</hi> where he was ſeen ſet upon a chariot richer then the Indies, and brighter then the Sun; that ſilence of our ſins is a triumph which exceeds that of the <hi>Grand Caeſar,</hi> when he cauſed himſelf to be drawn by forty Elephants unto the Capitol, (the glorious place of reception of the Roman Conquerours,) after he had obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the honour of 24. Battels; that ſilence is a triumph which excels that of a famous Queen of <hi>Egypt,</hi> when ſhe made her entrance into <hi>Cecilia,</hi> where ſhe was admired in a moſt glorious ſhip, which was ſo rich that no man could judge of the price; for in theſe triumphs ambition did ſit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on its throne, but in our Chriſtian triumph, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, juſtice, and charity ſit upon their thrones; happy ſilence then, that filleth men with grace!
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61843:36"/>happy ſilence, that procures us celeſtial honours, ſpiritual pleaſures, and incorruptible riches! happy ſilence that conducts us to eternal life! let us em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, while we are in our mortal bodies, that we may hereafter enjoy the eternal Crown of glory, with the ſcepter of immortality, which I wiſh you in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>To whom with the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit, be aſcribed all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, now and for evermore,</hi> Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:37"/>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:61843:37"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right Worſhipfull and my much Honoured Friend Sir <hi>JOSEPH PAINE</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Juſtice of Peace in the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> and Colonel of the Foot Regiment in <hi>Norwich, Health and Happineſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our great Civility to all, and in particular to my ſelf, gives me an aſſurance that you will kindly accept that which I here preſent your Worſhip; even a Sermon in which I hope the meanneſs and lowneſs of the ſtile, will not any ways diminiſh the excellency of the matter, <hi>viz.</hi> our <hi>Saviours Body,</hi> which you ſpiritually feed upon every Communion
<pb facs="tcp:61843:38"/>day, nay continually, ſeeing we feed upon it in our Celeſtial Meditations of Chriſt; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire therefore your Worſhip to look upon the Matter not on the Work it ſelf, being not worthy of your Acceptance: Indeed Sir, I had not aſſumed the boldneſs to offer this Preſent unto you, if I had not been ſure of your ſingular Goodneſs; I have had of it ſo much Experience, that it ſhould be a kind of crime to queſtion it; and indeed a true Subject of the Glorious <hi>Monarch of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as your Worſhip is, and hath always been, will not diſdain that which an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour offereth him, ſeeing that the Great <hi>Charles</hi> refuſeth not ſuch things from the moſt inferiour Perſon amongſt his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Truly Sir, the Obligations which I owe you are ſo great, that I am obliged to let others know the Civilities I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from your Noble and Generous Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and by your means from your moſt worthy Family; for I have nothing elſe to
<pb facs="tcp:61843:38"/>preſent you with, but the acknowledgement of your great courteſie, which I being ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, cannot but preſent my Prayers to the Almighty God of Heaven for your and your Families Proſperity, remaining with all the ſincerity of my heart,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble Servant,
<hi>James Le Frane.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:39"/>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:61843:39"/>
                  <head>Chriſts Sacramental Preſence, <hi>AGAINST</hi> Tranſubſtantiation <hi>and</hi> Conſubſtantiation; <hi>Delivered in a Sermon Preached at Great S.</hi> Peters <hi>in</hi> Norwich.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>S. MAT. 26.26.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>This is my body.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S we cannot but ſee the effects of the divine Goodneſs, if we contemplate this Univerſe, where God manifeſteth himſelf unto us by the marks of his Divinity and power, which there he engraved as the grand Apoſtle tels us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. ſaying, that <hi>the inviſible things of God, even his eternal power and Godhead, are clearly ſeen from, or, by the creation of the world:</hi> ſo we cannot but admire the great love of the Almighty God towards us, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that he made us the nobleſt of all his ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures, having printed <hi>in man the ſacred i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of himſelf,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> tels us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. and incloſed in him the being of all the created na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for man hath a corporal being with the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61843:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtars, Elements and Mettals; life with herbs, plants and trees; ſenſe with birds, beaſts and fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; and intelligence with angels; and ſo if the Philoſophers called juſtly man <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>a little world,</hi> me thinks they had much better ſaid if they had called him the <hi>great world;</hi> for what is in heaven or earth in compariſon of him, for whom they were created; <hi>they ſhall paſs</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> tels us, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. but <hi>man</hi> that noble creature ſhall <hi>remain for ever:</hi> it is true, that the conſideration of the Univerſe gives us a ſublime conception of our Creatour; but if we conſider within our ſelves, we ſhall ſee that we are the ſubject of all the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous effects of his providence; for in man his admirable power, goodneſs, and wiſdom did moſt gloriouſly appear, as the Royall Prophet tels us in the 8. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> ſaying, being raviſhed in admiration, <hi>thou haſt crowned him with glory and honour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But man in the eſtate of his integrity, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering himſelf ſo glorious, pride appeared and ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited him to ſit upon the throne of his maſter; and this glorious creature being overcome by that monſtrous ſollicitation, in his deſire to be like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, did become the moſt odious of all the creatures, and which is the higheſt of all miſeries, he became the ſlave of the Prince of darkneſs, ſo that of himſelf he could not return into the favour of his God, if God had not ſent his bleſſed Son our onely Redeemer into the world, to appeaſe his anger by the ſatisfaction he gave to his divine ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61843:40"/>for our ſins, which is ſuch a favour unto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting ſinners, that they muſt never be without a ſacrifice of thankſ-giving.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, by another effect of his divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God preſents unto us the great benefit of our redemption, by the continual preaching of the Goſpel; and confirms and ſeals it by the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the holy Sacraments, and eſpecially that of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which is a Sacrament of his death and paſſion, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. ſaying, <hi>as often as you eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye do ſhew the Lords death till he come;</hi> which Sacrament is mentioned in our Text, for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt ſpeaking of its inſtitution, after the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the Paſsover, ſaith, <hi>as they</hi> (the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) <hi>were eating, Jeſus took bread, and bleſſed it, broke it, and gave it to his diſciples,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Take and eat, this is my body;</hi> which words I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to entertain you with by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the bleſſed Spirit, and for a clear intelligence of them we ſhall conſider three things in our Text.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the <hi>Subject</hi> of the propoſition, <hi>this.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the <hi>Attribute, My body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the <hi>copula, is,</hi> which joyneth the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> with the <hi>Attribute, This is my body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>this,</hi> which is a demonſtrative pronoun, is taken in this place, not adectively but ſubſtantive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and for its explanation, you muſt obſerve, that <hi>this</hi> doth not ſignifie an <hi>uncertain individuum,</hi> or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:61843:41"/>a ſubſtance indefinitely, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> will have it; for if it were ſo <hi>this</hi> ſhould demonſtrate another ſubſtance as well as that of the body of Chriſt; neither doth <hi>this</hi> ſignifie or demonſtrate the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, <hi>the body of Chriſt,</hi> as if <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> ſhould be the ſame with <hi>it,</hi> as <hi>Scotus</hi> ſpeaks; for if it were ſo, the propoſition ſhould be identical, &amp; ſhould ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie nothing elſe, but <hi>this body of Chriſt is the body of Chriſt,</hi> which is abſurd; nor is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this</hi> to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of that which had been bread, as if ſome body, ſpeaking of that which <hi>Moſes</hi> held with his hand, which had been a rod, ſhould ſay, <hi>this is a ſerpent,</hi> or <hi>that,</hi> which was <hi>water at the marriage in Cana,</hi> is <hi>wine;</hi> for if it were ſo there ſhould have been a ſenſible converſion of the bread into the body of Chriſt, as there was in the changing of the rod into a ſerpent, and of the water into wine: nor is that Pronoun <hi>this</hi> taken adverbially for <hi>hic here,</hi> as thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will confeſs with us: for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> is referred to the bread which Chriſt took, broke, and gave to his diſciples, and ſo demonſtrates not a common but ſacramental bread, where the ſubſtance and quality remaining, the common uſe is onely changed into a ſacred one, as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth teach us.</p>
                  <p>And it matters not that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>bread</hi> is of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculine gender, for by the rule of the Grammar, when the ſubſtantive is underſtood, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the adjective muſt be the neuter gender, by way of a ſubſtantive, in thoſe things that are
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61843:41"/>without life; and ſo we may ſay, <hi>hoc eſt terra, this thing is earth,</hi> &amp; <hi>that</hi> is uſed ſomtimes in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, as thoſe that underſtand Greek may ſee in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.19. where the Apoſtle ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>for this is grace,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> being neuter, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> feminine; but it is ſo clear, that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this</hi> demonſtrates the <hi>bread</hi> which our bleſſed Saviour broke, and gave his diſciples, that the grand Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> cals it ſo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. <hi>the bread which we break, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> and in <hi>cha.</hi> 11. after he had told the <hi>Corinthians, that he had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them that which he had received from the Lord,</hi> that is, the manner of the adminiſtration of the Sacrament, ſaith, 26, 27, 28. <hi>as often as ye eat this bread and drink this cup, ye do ſhew the Lords death till he come; wherefore whoſoever ſhall eat this bread and drink this cup,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but let a man examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread;</hi> and if we call antiquity to witneſs, <hi>Tertullian</hi> will tell us in his Book againſt the <hi>Jews, Nos audiamus panem quem fregit Dominus eſse corpus Salvatoris; Let us hear that the bread which Chriſt broke is the body of our Saviour;</hi> which you muſt underſtand ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally; ſo S. <hi>Jerome ad Hebidiam,</hi> moreover, in the ſame ſenſe, <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 57. ſaith, that our Lord taking bread, confeſſed it to be his body; and <hi>Theodoret. dial.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. teacheth us, that in the exhibition of the myſteries, Chriſt called bread his body <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>The Councils alſo ſhew us the verity of our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61843:42"/>for the 37. <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Code</hi> of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of the Councils of <hi>Africa,</hi> tels us, that in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly places where Divine Service is celebrated, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more is offered but the body and bloud of Chriſt, <hi>hoc eſt, panis &amp; vinum aquâ mixtum,</hi> that is, bread and wine mingled with water, ſo the Council in <hi>Trullo</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> with the Council of <hi>Neocaeſarea,</hi> which forbids certain Prieſts to give the bread and cup <hi>coram Epiſcopo</hi> before a Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>And I wonder to hear thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> cavil ſo much at that word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> when they amongſt themſelves are not agreed upon it; for they diſpute among themſelves about the conſecration of the bread which Chriſt gave his diſciples; ſome ſay with the Greeks as thoſe of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and other Doctours of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> till theſe laſt times of Cardinal <hi>Cajetan,</hi> that the Conſecration was made by the bleſſing of Chriſt upon the bread, otherwiſe ſaith <hi>Chriſtophorus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Caeſarea, lib. de corr. Theol. Shol.</hi> that Propoſition, <hi>This is my body,</hi> had not been true, for if in that time the bread had not been changed by the bleſſing of Chriſt upon the bread, Chriſt had commanded his diſciples to take and eat bread; others with <hi>Cardinal Bellar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>min. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>de Euchar. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. ſay, that theſe words, <hi>This is my body,</hi> were as they are now the words of the Conſecration; and if we farther preſs them to tell us in what time the body of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:61843:42"/>Chriſt is in the Sacrament under the accidents as they ſpeak, they will anſwer with their angelical Doctor, <hi>Aqu. p.</hi> 3. <hi>qu.</hi> 75. <hi>ar.</hi> 7. <hi>ad</hi> 1. that it is when the laſt ſyllable <hi>um,</hi> of thoſe words <hi>hoc eſt enim corpus meum,</hi> is pronounced, <hi>toto tempore praeceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſubſtantiâ panis exiſtente,</hi> being onely before the ſubſtance of the bread; from whence it appears, that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> demonſtrates the bread, becauſe the laſt ſyllable was not yet pronounced, when Chriſt ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> as they confeſs with us; then let us ſay <hi>this bread is my body,</hi> which obligeth me to paſs to the <hi>attribute, my body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We need not to ſtay long upon the explication of Chriſts body mentioned in my Text, for you are not ignorant, that here by the <hi>body of Chriſt</hi> you muſt underſtand not his <hi>myſtical body,</hi> of which it is ſpoken, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27. <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23. for the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical body of our Saviour, which is, the <hi>Church,</hi> was not given or broken for us, but the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>natural body</hi> of Chriſt which <hi>was broken and given for her and her children,</hi> according to that of the <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28. where you ſee, that <hi>Chriſt hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Church with his own bloud, out of every kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and tongue, and people, and nation,</hi> Rev. 5.9. for you reade in S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.19. <hi>this is my body which is given for you,</hi> and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.24. <hi>this is my body which is broken for you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But for a better illuſtration of this our aſſertion, we muſt conſider the <hi>copula,</hi> which is the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>is,</hi> which joyneth the ſubject <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61843:43"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and obſerve that here it is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not properly and in its native ſignification, but figuratively and repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively, whatſoever <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth ſay to the contrary; for <hi>diſparatum de diſparato propriè dici non poteſt ſed ſiguratè,</hi> and therefore when there is any propoſition made of two divers and diſperate things, that propoſition muſt be improper &amp; figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, as our Propoſition <hi>this is my body, is;</hi> for the <hi>bread</hi> &amp; <hi>body</hi> of Chriſt being two divers and diſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate things, that Propoſition muſt be <hi>tropical</hi> &amp; <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative,</hi> where the cauſe of it is in the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which is taken in this place, for to ſignifie or to be the ſigne, as it is taken often in the Scripture, as you may ſee <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.26, 27. where it is ſaid, that <hi>ſeven kine are ſeven years,</hi> that is to ſay, ſignifie 7. years, and ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. we reade <hi>that ten horns are ten kings,</hi> that is to ſay ſignifie ten Kings; but ſpecially the verb <hi>to be</hi> is taken in that ſenſe, when it is queſtion of a Sacrament, as you may ſee, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. where we read this, the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion is my Covenant,</hi> thas is to ſay, the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion doth ſignifie or is the ſigne of my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. it is ſaid that the Lamb is the Lords Paſsover, <hi>it is the Lords Paſsover,</hi> that is, the ſigne of the Lords Paſsover, for the Lamb could not be properly the Lords Paſsover, and ſo amongſt the Jews was called our Saviour, as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr</hi> relates in his Dialogue, <hi>cum Thryp.</hi> for he ſaith, that <hi>Eſdras</hi> ſpeaking to the people,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61843:43"/>ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>this Paſsover is our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi> and indeed that was made ready for Chriſt by appropriation, for he was the <hi>lamb ſlain from the beginning of the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. tels us, <hi>that the rock was Chriſt,</hi> which was not in ſubſtance, but in ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſaith the Authour of the <hi>queſt.</hi> on <hi>Levit.</hi> then, <hi>this is my body,</hi> is as much as to ſay, <hi>this is the ſigne of my body,</hi> which is confirmed by S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> againſt the <hi>Manichee Adimantinus,</hi> for (ſaith he) Chriſt doubted not to ſay, <hi>this is my body, Cum da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret ſiguram corporis ſui</hi> when he gave the ſigne of his body; nay, the Council of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> held <hi>anno</hi> 756. condemning the images, accidentally ſpeaks of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and ſaith the ſubſtance of the bread is an image of our Saviour, and the gloſs of the Roman decree upon the Canon, <hi>hoc eſt, diſt.</hi> 2. tells us, that the celeſtial Sacrament which truly repreſents the fleſh of our Saviour is called his body but <hi>impropriè,</hi> impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, for it is ſo called <hi>non in ret veritate, ſed in myſterii ſignificatione,</hi> Chriſt being there repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and ſignified.</p>
                  <p>Now brethren obſerve, that the bread is called <hi>the body of Chriſt</hi> by reaſon of its analogy with it, for according to that of S. <hi>Auſtin, Ep.</hi> 23. <hi>ad Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facium,</hi> if the Sacraments had not ſome likeneſs or reſemblance with the things of which they are Sacraments, <hi>omnino ſacramenta non eſſent,</hi> they ſhould not at all be Sacraments, <hi>ex hac autem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudine
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61843:44"/>plerumque etiam ipſarum rerum nomina accipiunt,</hi> and from that reſemblance, they aſſume oftentimes the names of thoſe things which they do repreſent unto us; and indeed as the bread re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in our bodies nouriſheth them; ſo the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt received by faith nouriſheth our ſouls; as our bodies encreaſe and have ſtrength by the eating of the bread, ſo have our ſouls their grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto a perfect man, <hi>unto the meaſure of the ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> and receive their ſtrength againſt all temptations, by the ſpiritual eating of our Saviour, the celeſtial bread which is the true meat of our ſouls; as the bread preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth our corporal life, ſo the body of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in us the ſpiritual life, as our Saviour teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in the Goſpel, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.53. ſaying, <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud, ye have no life in you;</hi> where you ſee, that the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Sacramental ſigne, with the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, is not local but relative, in regard the ſigne repreſents to us the things by it ſignified.</p>
                  <p>But although theſe things are ſo clear, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of that explication, for they underſtand by theſe words <hi>this is my body,</hi> a proper and not figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative propoſition, which ſhews us a real <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> of the ſubſtance of the bread into the ſubſtance of the body of Chriſt, remaining onely the accidents, that is, what you ſee of the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated bread, ſo that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> demonſtrates the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61843:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>body of Chriſt, <hi>ſub ſpeciebus vel accidentibus panis,</hi> under the accidents of the bread; for (ſay they) this Propoſition, <hi>this is my body,</hi> is the Will and Teſtament of our bleſſed Lord, where ſigures are not admitted as being ſomething obſcure.</p>
                  <p>But firſt I have ſhewed you, that this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>this is my body,</hi> is not a proper ſaying, but a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative one, by the nature of all the Sacraments, which are the ſame in ſignification and uſe in the New, as they were in the Old Teſtament, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> evidently teacheth us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.23. for (ſaith he) they <hi>were all baptized in the cloud, and did all eat,</hi> not onely among them, but alſo <hi>with us,</hi> the <hi>ſame ſpiritual meat;</hi> and ſo S. <hi>Auſtin. lib. de utilit. poenit.</hi> ſaith, that whoſoever apprehended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt in the Manna, <hi>cundem quem nos cibum ſpiritualem comederunt,</hi> did eat the ſame ſpiritual meat, which we do eat, which ſaying of <hi>Auſtin</hi> made ſuch an impreſſion on the Jeſuit <hi>Maldonat,</hi> that he ſaid, if S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> had lived in his time he had changed his opinion, ſeeing that the interpretation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants which he calls <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> is almoſt the ſame. <hi>Maldonat.</hi> on S. <hi>Job.</hi> 6.50. <hi>num.</hi> 80, 81.</p>
                  <p>As for what they ſay, that it is a Teſtament, we confeſs it with them, but we ſay, that the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our bleſſed Saviours Will, is figurative and tropical, as it doth appear by what we have ſaid, and by S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.20. where you read, after Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>this is my body, this cup is the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in my bloud,</hi> which is confirmed by S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:61843:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. for it is evident, that the cup was not the teſtament; and it will not much ſerve them, to ſay, that this paſſage hath two expreſſions, where the firſt muſt be rendred ſo, <hi>this is the cup, the new teſtament in mybloud,</hi> the ſecond, <hi>this cup is the new teſtament in my bloud,</hi> becauſe the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>is,</hi> is expreſt in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and omitted in S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. for although in the firſt expreſſion the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>is,</hi> is taken by them properly, becauſe it was a cup that Chriſt preſented to his diſciples, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs they confeſs a ſigure is in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for they ſay, that in that expreſſion the cup is taken for what was in it, and that the teſtament is that by which we have right to the Covenant, but it is certain, that that which they will have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, is but the ſame thing, and the ſame Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in that paſſage of S. <hi>Luke</hi> &amp; of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> to ſignifie that the cup, or the wine in the cup, is the ſigne of the New Teſtament, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Concerning tropical locutions, which are not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted (as they ſay) in teſtaments, as being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing obſcure, I ſay, that it is not always ſo, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they themſelves uſe them for illuſtration, and it is clear enough that ſigures have places in teſtaments; let them conſider the teſtament of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 49. that of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 33. and that of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. and they ſhall with us ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them to be allegorical; moreover, beſides the Civilians obſerve, that in mens Teſtaments
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61843:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>there are oftentimes ſigurative expreſſions, for which they have ſome reſtrictions, which cauſe them to ſay, that in Teſtaments they muſt not come to a proper or ſtrict ſignification of words, <hi>Cum plerumque abuſivè loquuntur teſtatores,</hi> ſeeing that the Teſtators oftentimes ſpeak improperly; I ſay if the humane Teſtaments ſhould be ſo plain, that there ſhould be no figures, it would not follow, that there ſhould be none in divine and ſpiritual Teſtaments; for in a humane Teſtament there are nothing but Legacies and expreſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, which ought to be plainly underſtood; but in a divine and ſpiritual Teſtament there are myſteries to exerciſe our underſtandings, our faith, hope and patience, as the Learned men moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly obſerve, there are ſome things for this life, and ſome things for the life to come, ſome things are clearly ſeen, and ſome things darkly perceived: Moreover, in humane Wills men ought to ſpeak plainly, becauſe they can ſpeak no more when they are dead, but in the ſpiritual Teſtament which is here mentioned, the Teſtator can ſpeak after his death, as you know that he did, and doth truly know it, for Chriſt after his aſcenſion into the glorious Palace of his Father, ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke unto S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was the grand Perſecutour of his ſacred members, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4, 5. as now by his holy Spirit, he ſpeaks unto us, and makes the Church underſtand as much as he pleaſeth, and as much as is neceſſary for the glory of his Father, and her eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:61843:46"/>
                  <p>By this you may ſee, that our Propoſition <hi>[this is my body]</hi> importeth nothing elſe, but this bread ſignifies or is the ſigne of my body; and indeed if the body of Chriſt were corporally in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the accidents, it ſhould there be paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that is, ſubject to alteration and ſufferings; or impaſſible, that is not ſubject to any alterations or ſufferings; but the body of Chriſt cannot be there paſſible or ſubject to any alteration; for if it were ſo, he ſhould be there with all his dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in order to a certain place (otherwiſe he could not ſuffer as they will confeſs with us) and ſo the body of Chriſt could be divided, which they will not grant in the Sacrament, ſaying, that it is <hi>totum in tota hoſtia, &amp; totum in qualibet parte hoſtiae;</hi> wholly in the hoſt, and wholly in every part of it; and although <hi>Pope Nicholas</hi> forced <hi>Berengarius</hi> to recant in thoſe words) <hi>I Berengarius aſſirm, that Chriſts ſleſh is ſenſually handled and broken by the Prieſts hands in the Sacrament, and grinded by the teeth of the ſaithfull;</hi>) nevertheleſs they will not admit of that expreſſion, and confeſs it is not ſo; inſomuch that the gloſs on the Canon <hi>de Conſecr. diſtinct.</hi> 2. <hi>cap. Ego Berengarius;</hi> affirms it to be a worſe hereſie then that of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> unleſs it be ſoberly underſtood, for generally they hold, that Chriſts body is in the Sacrament <hi>ſub ſpeciebus panis,</hi> impaſſibly; which yet cannot be, for if it were ſo, his body had been a glorious body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his reſurrection (impaſſibility being one of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:61843:46"/>the chief qualities of a glorious body, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with us) for you know that Chriſt did cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the holy Sacrament before his death; moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver if the body of Chriſt were impaſſible under the accidents in the Sacrament I would ask them (the Apoſtles having conſecrated at his death) whether <hi>Chriſts body</hi> had been alive or no in the Sacrament; I ſuppoſe they will not ſay that it had been alive; for in the ſame time it had been alive in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the accidents, and dead in the grave, which is a manifeſt contradiction; nor dead I hope, for that ſhould be contrary to their aſſertion of Chriſt impaſſible in the Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>But give me leave to go yet further and ſay, that if Chriſt were corporally in the Sacrament under the accidents, his body had been viſible, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it had been glorious; for Chriſt ſpeaking to his diſciples after his reſurrection, ſaid, <hi>behold my hands and my feet, and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones as you ſee me have;</hi> but as you ſee nothing in the breaking of a conſecrated hoſt but bread (beſides you cannot diſcern a conſecrated hoſt from another that is not, as I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when I was in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) it follows, that the body of Chriſt is not in the Sacrament under the accidents, paſſibly nor impaſſibly; more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, if Chriſt were in the Sacrament <hi>corporally,</hi> he had eaten himſelf, if (as ſome of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> confeſs,) Chriſt did communicate with his diſciples which is very probable, as you may ſee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61843:47"/>by S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29. where Chriſt, after the exhibition of the bread and cup, ſaith, I <hi>ſay unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine, till that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly I ſay, that if Chriſt is in the Hoſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally, his body which according to them remains no longer in their bodies then the ſubſtance of the bread (if there it were) ſhould remain ceaſing to be under the accidents, is reduced to nothing, or changed into another ſubſtance, or remains wholly; but is not reduced to nothing, nor changed into another ſubſtance, according to them; for if it were ſo Chriſts body ſhould be corruptible, and could be changed into any ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inſenſible ſubſtance, which cannot be ſaid without diſhonour to our bleſſed Saviour; to ſay that the body of Chriſt remains wholly, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved or maintained without abſurdity; for I ask whether that body remains in our bodies or goeth to heaven? they will not ſay, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in our bodies, for ſome ſhould have as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they have received the Sacrament; nor will they ſay, that it goeth to heaven, for the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of ſo many millions of Chriſts by the multiplication of their conſecrations, cannot be admitted in heaven, without abſurdity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to the holy Scripture, which tels us, that <hi>there is but one body, and one Chriſt in heaven;</hi> it follows then that the body of Chriſt is not under the accidents, which obligeth me to ſay with <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus,</hi>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:61843:47"/>that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath too late determined the <hi>tranſubſtantiation</hi> (the truth being known before, as <hi>Scotus</hi> and their Learned <hi>Tonſtal. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Euch. pag.</hi> 46. inſinuates) and indeed this Propoſition <hi>this is my body,</hi> ſignifies nothing elſe, but this Sacramental bread is the ſigne of my body.</p>
                  <p>But it ſeems, that ſome others will not yield to our aſſertion; for the <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſay in defence of their <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> that in this <hi>bread,</hi> under this <hi>bread,</hi> and with this <hi>bread</hi> is <hi>the body of Chriſt;</hi> for they pretend by their ubiquity, that the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature of Chriſt is every where, but me thinks they ſhould have better obſerved the words of our bleſſed Saviour, who onely ſaith <hi>this is my body,</hi> and not <hi>in this bread, with this bread,</hi> and <hi>under this bread is my body;</hi> let us keep cloſe to his words, Chriſt being the truth it ſelf; and indeed <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>this,</hi> doth not ſigniſie <hi>in, with,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> but onely demonſtrates the ſingular ſubſtance of the Sacramental bread, as being the ſigne of his body, truly natural, viſible, palpable, and in order to a certain place ſinite; which they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand to be not natural, not viſible, not palpable, and every where not ſinite, although not infinite; which is ſuch a body that Chriſt never had, for after his reſurrection, his body was palpable, viſible, and in one place at once as well as before; and that will not ſave them to ſay he was but in one place at once viſibly, but every where inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, for Chriſt ſhews that a body is always viſible
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61843:48"/>of its nature, ſaying, S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection <hi>handle me, and ſee me, for a ſpirit hath not ſleſh and bones, as you ſee me have:</hi> where you may obſerve, that Chriſt diſtinguiſheth the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane body from the ſpirit by its viſibleneſs and palpability after its glorious reſurrection; moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the aſcenſion of Chriſt into heaven diverſly expreſt by the Evangeliſts, teacheth us, that the body of Chriſt cannot be in two places at once vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly nor inviſibly, for S. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.19. ſaith, that Chriſt after he had ſpoken unto his Diſciples, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>was received up,</hi> which could not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his divine nature, which is every where, but according to this humane nature, which cannot be in ſeveral places at once; S. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, 24.51. that Chriſt <hi>parted from them,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>and was carried up,</hi> that is, according to his humane nature, which onely was capable of local motion, by which we leave one place to go to another, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.9. it is ſaid, <hi>that while the apoſtles beheld</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> he <hi>was taken up,</hi> which is alſo ſaid in regard of his humane nature, and ſo the Greek Fathers judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſpeak, when they ſay, that the aſcenſion of our Saviour is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>his aſsumption in ſleſh:</hi> Moreover we reade in the 3. Chapter of the <hi>Acts</hi> 21. <hi>verſe, that the heavens muſt contain him until the reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tution of all things,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſhews, that the humane nature of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cannot be in two places at once, for when
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61843:48"/>Chriſt ſhall come upon the earth to judge the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, he ſhall in regard of his humane nature leave heaven where he now is.</p>
                  <p>But let us go further, and give me leave to ſay, that if the humane nature of Chriſt be every where; it was, or in the Eſtate of his humiliation, from the very inſtant of his conception, as ſome <hi>Lutherans</hi> do affirm; or in his eſtate of exaltation from the very inſtant of his reſurrection, or that of his ſeſſion at the right hand of his Father, as ſome other <hi>Lutherans</hi> ſay; but I cannot perceive, that it was in his eſtate of humiliation, from the very inſtant of his conception, for if it were ſo, the body of Chriſt had not onely been formed in the womb of the bleſſed Virgin, but alſo in every womans womb, even the moſt wicked; for in that very inſtant, according to thoſe of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion it was every where, nay, more then that, Chriſt could not have been born of her, for in the very inſtant of his conception he was in every part of the world, his ſoul could not have been ſeparated from his body, being every where; and ſo he could not have died for us, for ſo long as the ſoul remains in the body, we cannot ſay properly, a man is dead, but onely we conceive a ſuſpenſion of the vital actions: moreover, Chriſt had been in heaven before his reſurrection, according to his humane nature, being every where in the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of his conception, which agrees not with the Scripture, which ſhews us the aſcenſion of Chriſt
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61843:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>into heaven to be after his death; nor can I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that it was every where in the ſtate of his exaltation from the very inſtant of his reſurrection, or that of his ſeſſion at the right hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for if it were ſo, ſuch an alteration in humane nature could not have been without a wonderfull ſigne (as being ſo prodigious) that it cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived without the deſtruction of Chriſts body; &amp; indeed it is impoſſible to apprehend a thing cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed in a place, when it is not in a certain place fully contained, but every where in all the places of the ſuperiour and inferiour world, which is the manner of being in a place, that is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto God, privatively to all others, for in all the School-Divinity, in the old Philoſophy, and in nature, there are but three natural proper waies of being in a place, <hi>circumſcriptivè, deſinitivè, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletivè,</hi> where you muſt obſerve, that all corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſubſtances are circumſcriptively in a place, all the ſpiritual but finite ſubſtances, as angels and ſouls of men ſeparated from their bodies defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and God alone is repletively in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; for it is that manner of being in a place by which God is diſtinguiſhed from his creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God not his creatures, <hi>nec loco includitur, nec loco excluditur, nec loco circumſcribitur, nec lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co definitur,</hi> is neither included in a place, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from any.</p>
                  <p>Indeed I cannot imagine how it came to paſs, that the body of Chriſt which was before in order
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61843:49"/>to a certain place circumſcriptively, ſhould be now every where, and made <hi>ex finito non finitum,</hi> from finite not ſinite; beſides you muſt know that Chriſts body is not every where, becauſe it is a glorified body, for if it were ſo, all glorified bodies would be every where; nor becauſe the humane nature is united with the divine, to the perſon of the Son of God, for it was ſo from the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of his conception, which teacheth us, that the <hi>body of Chriſt</hi> is not <hi>in the bread, with the bread,</hi> and <hi>under the bread;</hi> but if you inſtance, and ſay, then follows the ſeparation of the two natures of Chriſt; I anſwer, that ſuch a thing doth not follow; for although the humane nature of Chriſt be not every where, yet the divine nature is, and therefore it cannot be ſeparate from the humane nature; then it remains, that, <hi>this is my body,</hi> is nothing elſe but this <hi>bread is the ſigne and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now it may be that you will ſay, by all what you have ſaid we cannot well gather how Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament, but rather it ſeems that you deny the preſence of our Lord in it: To which I anſwer, and ſay, that Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament; but you muſt obſerve, that by the Sacrament I underſtand the Sacramental acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>in concreto,</hi> comprehending the ſigne and the thing ſignified, according to which ſenſe our Learned Doctours uſe to ſay, that <hi>Chriſt is not preſent in the bread, but in the Sacrament,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61843:50"/>in the Sacramental action the thing ſignified Chriſt our bleſſed Saviour is given together with the ſigne to the beleever; but obſerve that Chriſt is preſent in the holy Sacrament, not locally but ſacramentally, <hi>ſignificativè, ſpiritualiter &amp; virtualiter,</hi> ſigniſicatively, ſpiritually, and virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; for you muſt know that beſides the local preſence of a thing, of which we have ſpoken, and which we have ſaid was threefold, there are alſo preſences of 3. ſeveral ſorts, which are of another nature, for there is a ſymbolical and ſignificative preſence, which is when a thing is preſent unto us by ſome mark or ſigne, as our brother and ſiſter is preſent unto us by their picture; the ſecond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is a ſpiritual preſence, which is when by faith things that are not preſent locally, are made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſpiritually, as the day of Chriſt was preſent to <hi>Abraham,</hi> although it came to paſs long after him, above 2000 years after, as we reade S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.36. where Chriſt ſaith unto the Jews, <hi>Abraham rejoyced to ſee my day</hi> (whether it was his birth or his death upon the Croſs it matters not) <hi>he ſaw it by ſaith, and was glad,</hi> as now we ſee and touch Chriſt; for as S. <hi>Ambroſe de Sacrament. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4. ſaith, <hi>fide lang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur, ſide videtur, non langitur cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, non oculis comprehenditur;</hi> Chriſt the bread of life is toucht by ſaith, and ſeen by faith, and that ſpiritually not corporally; which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirmed by Chriſt himſelf, S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. where you may obſerve againſt <hi>Bellarmin.</hi> and others
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61843:50"/>of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that Chriſt ſpeaks <hi>de re Sacramenti,</hi> of the thing ſignified in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſleſh and bloud of Chriſt which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by ſaith; not <hi>de ipſis ſignis,</hi> of the external ſignes of it, which we corporally and materially receive; the third preſence is a preſence of vertue, which is, when a thing which is far from a place is nevertheleſs preſent by its vertue, as you may ſee in the Sun, which being far diſtant from the Earth, yet is preſent unto it by its vertue.</p>
                  <p>Now you muſt know, that all theſe preſences are to be found in the holy Sacrament; for Chriſt with his body and bloud is there preſent, firſt ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolically and ſignificatively, for he is repreſented unto us by the external ſignes of bread and wine; ſecondly ſpiritually, becauſe in the ſpiritual rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of the Sacrament we apply unto our ſelves the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt by faith, and ſo we are united unto him, and ſpiritually nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his body and bloud; thirdly, Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament with his body and bloud virtually; for in the worthy participation of the Sacrament we receive the fruit and vertue of his death and paſſion, but obſerve, that the firſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt which is ſymbolical, is given to the wicked, but the ſpiritual and virtual preſence to the faithfull; although then the body of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is as far from us as heaven is from the earth, yet the real Sacramental preſence remains, for you may know that <hi>preſentia alicujus rei non
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61843:51"/>opponitur diſtantiaeſed abſentiae,</hi> the preſence of a thing is not oppoſed to diſtance but abſence, and ſo you may ſee, that theſe preſences do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict our aſſertion, but do rather confirm it, and oblige us to ſay, that, <hi>this is my body,</hi> ſignifies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but this bread is the ſigne and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my body.</p>
                  <p>Now let us conclude with Application, and learn from thence the great and exceeding affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lord towards us, who would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire upon the Croſs, before he had given us the precious token of our redemption; was it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for our bleſſed Saviour to aſſume our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature, to manifeſt in it his Father unto the corrupted world, and propoſe by it his ſacred counſel to ſinners? Was it not enough for our bleſſed Saviour to be made fleſh with the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and infirmities of a ſenſitive life, which makes us ſubject to hunger, thirſt, ſorrow, and death, to redeem thoſe who by their ſins were made a ſinfull fleſh? was it not enough for our bleſſed Saviour to accompliſh the law for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected ſinners, dye for their ſins, and riſe for their aſſurance? yea, we muſt truly ſay, that it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make us confeſs the inſinite love of our God towards us, and exclaim every one of us as the grand Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul Rom.</hi> 8. with a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards him who loved us; <hi>I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that neither death, nor liſe, nor angels, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61843:51"/>to come, nor beight, nor depth, nor any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſs our bleſſed Redeemer, knowing that ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> in which we have been all corrupted, our nature is ſo weak with its faculties, that we cannot well remember thoſe things which concern our ſalvation; hath ſhewed us another effect of his ſacred love; he gave us his Word that we may have continually before our eyes <hi>Jeſus Chriſt and him cruciſied,</hi> and left us the holy Sacraments, and ſpecially that of the Lords Supper, to ſeal unto our ſouls the great myſtery of our redemption, that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Chriſt did for us upon the Croſs; for as Chriſt himſelf ſaith, S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.19. <hi>this doin remembrance of me;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. <hi>as often as ye eat this bread and drink this cup, ye do ſhew the Lords death till he comes;</hi> remember then dear brethren that great and ſublime myſtery of our redemption, that in the reception of the holy Sacraments your ſouls may be ſealed with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſeal of the holy Ghoſt for your eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>But before you come to the ſacred banquet of our Lord (where his body and bloud is ſerved for our celeſtial meat and ſpiritual drink) prepare your ſelves, examine your life, and conſider your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward actions; to abhor the ſins and corruptions of them, that coming with a ſtrong
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61843:52"/>reſolution, to leave ſin and embrace that noble daughter of heaven, <hi>vertue,</hi> you may worthily participate of the Sacrament of the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt, for as S <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Let a man examine himſelf</hi> (not his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as many pretended Saints do) <hi>and ſo let him eat of that bread and drink of that cup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Remember that you go unto that ſacred ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet with reverence, and in the conſideration of your ſins go with humility, for Chriſt takes a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular pleaſure to dwell in the houſe of an humble Chriſtian; if he comes unto <hi>Zacheus</hi> his houſe, <hi>Zacheus</hi> muſt come down firſt, as you read S. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.5. <hi>Zacheus make haſte and come down, for to day I muſt abide at thy houſe;</hi> and ſo S. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.6. ſaith, that <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and giveth grace unto the humble:</hi> Let us come by faith, for it is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred mouth and ſpiritual hand with which we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the body and bloud of Jeſus Chriſt; as by faith we have a ſacred union with our bleſſed Saviour, let us not be Capernaical but Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, prepare not your teeth, beleeve and thou haſt eaten it, ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin;</hi> do you not ſay how ſhall I ſend my hands and arms to heaven? ſend your faith.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, remember that you come with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and not hypocritical repentance, that you may not be like unto <hi>Judas</hi> who kiſſed his Maſter to betray him; for you know that it is by that noble but ſorrowfull vertue, repentance, that we muſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61843:52"/>come unto that ſacred banquet of the lamb ſlain for our ſins, for we do not come unto that ſacred banquet as innocent unto the goodneſs of our God, but as repenting ſinners unto his grace; but brethren, you muſt be void of envy, hatred, and malice, leſt you ſhould take the holy Sacrament to your own condemnation, you know that it is a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of our union nor onely with Chriſt, but alſo amongſt our ſelves; for as the Apoſtle ſays, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 <hi>We who are many are one bread, and one body, for we are all partakers of that one bread:</hi> do ye not abſent your ſelves from that ſacred ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, leſt you entertain communion with the god of this world, and conſerve in your ſelves hatred and malice to your own deſtruction; indeed the more you abſent your ſelves from the Sacrament, the more will the devil keep you from it; ſo that at laſt ye will deſpiſe the holy Sacrament and procure to your ſelves a kinde of hardneſs to ſin.</p>
                  <p>But further give me leave to beſeech you to look upon the meat and drink of that bleſſed and ſacred banquet, Chriſt himſelf, whoſe body and bloud is precious meat and drink, Chriſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bread from whom we draw the ſpiritual wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of wiſdom, righteouſneſs, ſanctification and redemption: for as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Chriſt is made unto us wiſdom, righteouſneſs, ſanctiſication and redemption:</hi> Conſider thoſe that ſerve at that myſtical Table, the holy Angels, they ſerve but they eat not, the meat of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61843:53"/>Table is not for them, it is onely for repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinners; which things if you ſeriouſly look upon, I am ſure that you will endeavour with the grace of our God to prepare your ſelves for a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy reception of the Lords Supper, that you may be partakers not onely of the external ſignes and Sacramental bread, but alſo of Chriſt the thing ſignified by them, the heavenly bread, who will preſerve you from eternal death, and bring you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious kingdom of his Father, to enjoy after the ſacred banquet of grace, the glorious ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:53"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right Worſhipfull, Right Vertuous, and truly Religious, my much Honoured Friend <hi>WILLIAM ADAMS</hi> 
                     <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
                     <hi>Felicity and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Merit and high Repute of your Civility is as a Voice that is heard not onely in all the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where you have been, but in many others alſo which were not honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by your Preſence; <hi>Fama volat:</hi> and indeed whereſoever I come, I hear great Commendations of your Worſhip; The world ſaith, and that with Juſtice, that
<pb facs="tcp:61843:54"/>your Piety and Modeſty is incomparable, and an Example to the Nobility that lives far and near that Temple of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour where you have your Noble Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: But Sir, give me leave to ſay, that your Learning is not obſcure, and though you be young in years, yet you are old in Prudence; Nay, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that your Worſhip is indued with ſuch rare and eminent Qualities, that there be few among Perſons of Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy who do enjoy them; It is not then without Deſigne that I am ſollicitous to preſent the Spiritual Kingdom of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (againſt the Monarchical Reign of our <hi>Chiliaſtes</hi>) to your moſt piercing ſight; for having its Review and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation by ſo clear a Judgement, I ſhall not fear what Eye it may be expoſed to for its Cenſure; I hope, Sir, that you will receive this Sermon although not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your Acceptance, the which indeed I
<pb facs="tcp:61843:54"/>dare not queſtion, being fully perſwaded of your Affection towards me, which I ſhall ever acknowledge and highly eſteem, remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto death,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humble and obliged Servant,
James Le Franc.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:55"/>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:61843:55"/>
                  <head>Chriſt's and the Saints Reign: <hi>OR,</hi> The Millenaries Confuted. <hi>Delivered in a Sermon Preached at S.</hi> Andrews <hi>in</hi> Norwich.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REV. 20.4.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>And they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any matter hath ever required atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am perſwaded that you will confeſs, that this doth require it; for the learned Interpreters have ſo vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly expounded it, that it is difficult to determine our ſelves upon this Subject; Indeed I had not medled with it, if I had not perceived the errour of ſome of the common people, which follow ſome blinde leaders, whoſe ambition is to extoll themſelves, and break aſunder the Church of God to have ſome followers; for amongſt the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61843:56"/>Sectaries you ſee ſo many of them blinded by their ignorance, that they will rather chooſe a worldly reign then a Spiritual Kingdom, earth for heaven, and temporal delights for eternal pleaſures; but leaving them for a while upon their earthly Throne, give me leave to tell you, that this Chapter contains three principal parts.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of which regards the ſpace of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, under which Chriſt with his Saints ſhall reign upon the earth.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond includes the ſhort time in which <hi>Satan</hi> after the expiration of the thouſand years <hi>ſhall be looſed out of his priſon;</hi> from whence you may conſider what will be the condition of the world, when in that time you ſhall ſee it embroil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with diſſentions, wars and ſeductions, as you may ſee by the 8. and 9. <hi>ver.</hi> of our Chapter.</p>
                  <p>The third part teacheth us the <hi>general Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Univerſe,</hi> where the wicked ſhall be condemned to eternal puniſhment, and the godly declared the heirs of eternal felicity and glory.</p>
                  <p>But as our Text is under the firſt part of our Chapter, let me tell you, that S. <hi>John</hi> in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it brings in an <hi>angel</hi> which is <hi>Chriſt, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming down from heaven, having the key of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit, with a great chain in his hand to binde with it the dragon, which is the devil &amp; Satan, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, &amp; ſhut him up into the bottomleſs pit, with a ſeal upon him,</hi> to ſtay his power, and hinder his tyrannical Empire over the humane kinde, <hi>that he
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61843:56"/>may deceive the nations no more;</hi> where in the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den age of Satans chaining, you may conſider the condition of the faithfull and godly men, and ſee their conqueſts, triumphs, and victories over their enemies in their very puniſhments &amp; death, for the promulgation of the Goſpel, and the advancing of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt: for in the 4. <hi>ver.</hi> the beloved Diſciple of our Saviour S. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he ſaw thrones, and they</hi> (that is the Martyrs) <hi>ſate upon them; and I ſaw the ſouls of them that were beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus, and for the word of God, which had not worſhipped the</hi> Antichriſtian <hi>beaſt, neither his image, nor bad received his mark upon their foreheads, or in their hands;</hi> adding, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years:</hi> which are the words which I have choſen to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain you with by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the bleſſed Spirit; but for a clear intelligence of them I ſhall divide my Text into two parts, where in the firſt I ſhall ſpeak of the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>reign</hi> of the Saints with Chriſt in theſe words, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt;</hi> and in the ſecond part I ſhall ſhew you the <hi>duration</hi> of it, <hi>a thouſand years; and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>If we conſider the holy Scripture we may evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſee that our Saviour hath onely two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdoms; the one <hi>providential,</hi> which is that univerſal Soveraignty by which Chriſt mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61843:57"/>the affairs of all the whole world, both in heaven and earth; the other <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> which is that royal but celeſtial authority which he exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth over his people, <hi>the elect,</hi> which is that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in which the Saints or faithfull live and reign with Chriſt, as you may ſee in <hi>Revel.</hi> 5.10. where it is ſaid, <hi>that Chriſt hath made us unto our God kings and prieſts, that we may reign on the earth,</hi> or <hi>and we ſhall reign on the earth,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and that in a ſpiritual manner; ſo in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. we reade, that <hi>if by one mans offence death reigneth by one, much more they which receive abundance of grace ſhall reign in life by one Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and in our Text, <hi>and they lived and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Which makes me wonder at the <hi>Chiliaſts</hi> or <hi>Millenaries</hi> opinion, which gives our Saviour in this place of Scripture, as in many others, a third Kingdom which they call <hi>Monarchical;</hi> wherein Chriſt when he enters upon it, will govern as earthly Monarchs do, univerſally over the world, in a viſible and earthly glory and ſplendour, which is the perſonal reign which they give to our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, and which I obſerve to be diverſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by its aſſertors.</p>
                     <p>For the <hi>Jews</hi> perſwade themſelves, that at the poſſeſſion of that Kingdom, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be moſt ſplendidly reedified with the Temple, which according to them will be the third, Sacrifices of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered unto the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Marriages amongſt
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61843:57"/>themſelves moſt gloriouſly celebrated, and all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity and happineſs without any moleſtation or hindrance of their enemies enjoyed; ſo that they underſtand that reign of Jeſus Chriſt both carnal and ſpiritual.</p>
                     <p>Some ancient Doctours of the Chriſtian Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, as <hi>Juſtin. dialog. contra Tryphon. Lactantius ille, Firmianus, Tertullian,</hi> againſt <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, lib.</hi> 2. and others were of that opinion, that the Monarchical Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be adminiſtred in a ſpiritual manner without any bloudy ſacrifice or libation, without marriages or ſenſual pleaſures; for as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> (after his diſcourſe about the day of judgement, which he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) ſaith to <hi>Trypho</hi> the Jew, at that time we ſhall immolate true and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſacrifices, and offer praiſes and thankſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings unto our God, without any bloudy ſacrifice upon an altar.</p>
                     <p>Some hereticks as <hi>Cerinthius</hi> and <hi>Apollinaris</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that Monarchical Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt in a fleſhly manner, ſaying, that the Saints ſhould reign with Chriſt upon the earth, in all manner of voluptuous pleaſures, <hi>gulae &amp; luxuriae,</hi> of gluttony and wantonneſs, which perhaps may be the ſenſe of ſome of our Sectaries, although they pretend to interpret it of a viſible and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Monarchy, without any fleſhly and <hi>ſinfull vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lupty,</hi> as one <hi>Archer</hi> a London-Divine expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it.</p>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:61843:58"/>
                     <p>But I will not ſtay ſo long upon that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Kingdom, for we do not know ſuch a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the holy Scripture, attributed unto Chriſt, nor to the Saints, although you reade in my Text, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt;</hi> and indeed it is evident that the Scripture denies it, for we read S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.36. that Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Pilate, my Kingdom is not of this world;</hi> nor from hence, which manifeſtly contradicts the <hi>Chiliaſts</hi> or <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenaries</hi> opinion, for if Chriſt (as they ſay) will govern at that time as earthly Monarchs do in a worldly viſible and earthly glory, <hi>how is his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom not of this world?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, if there were ſuch a kingdom given to our Saviour, we ſhould have heard in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture of a third perſonal coming of Jeſus Chriſt, which we do not; for the Scripture makes onely mention of two perſonal comings of our bleſſed Saviour, where the firſt is his coming in humane weakneſs, to make us ſtrong againſt our powerfull enemies, the devil, the fleſh and the world; the ſecond his coming in majeſty and glory, to give judgement to the quick and dead after their reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and we confeſs in our Creed <hi>that from thence,</hi> that is, heaven, where Chriſt now is, <hi>he ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead,</hi> which is confirmed by the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> and <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, to whith we muſt keep cloſe, as being <hi>the ſaith which was once delivered to the Saints.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if ſome Millenaries will not underſtand
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61843:58"/>that Monarchical kingdom of our Saviour perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then that kingdom fals of it ſelf, for Chriſt now reigneth by his Spirit in the hearts of his regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Subjects, as they will confeſs with us, and they reign with him; for as our Text ſaith, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But further that Monarchical Kingdom of Chriſt cannot ſtand without two general corporal reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, the one of thoſe Saints which were dead before that perſonal coming of Chriſt, at which he ſhall take the adminiſtration of his Monarchical kingdom, the other at the end of the world at his ſinal coming to judgement, as they themſelves acknowledge, which is a thing that the Scripture makes no mention of; for the Word of God makes onely mention of one general corporal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, at the end of the world, as you may ſee <hi>Job</hi> 19.25. where it is ſaid by that moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Patriarch, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth, and though after my skin worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God;</hi> nay <hi>Martha</hi> as you reade S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.24. confeſſeth to Chriſt, that <hi>her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal riſe again in the reſurrection of the laſt day,</hi> and not at the day of the adminiſtration of Chriſts Monarchical kingdom; and you know that S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.52. ſaith, that <hi>in a moment, in the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye, we ſhall riſe at the laſt Trumpet;</hi> and ſo in our Creed we confeſs <hi>the refurrection,</hi> and not the <hi>reſurrections of the fleſh;</hi> and that will not ſerve
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61843:59"/>the Millinaries to ſay, that in our Chapter in the 5. <hi>ver.</hi> it appears clearly that there are two gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reſurrections of the fleſh, when we hear of a <hi>firſt reſurrection</hi> which inſinuates a <hi>ſecond</hi> one; for that firſt reſurrection which is mentioned there, is the reſurrection not of the body but of the ſoul, from the death of ſin to the life of grace, as S. <hi>Auſt.</hi> did well obſerve; I know that ſome take that firſt reſurrection for the glorious happineſs of the ſoul, by which ſhe alone paſſeth by the death of the body into eternal life, and that by the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding words of the 1. <hi>verſe,</hi> which are, <hi>but the reſt of the dead,</hi> that is, the wicked and reprobate, <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not again,</hi> &amp;c. becauſe they experimented in hell the firſt death and damnation, which is of the ſoul alone, which obligeth S. <hi>John</hi> to ſay in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Saints departed who are oppoſed to the wicked, <hi>this is the firſt reſurrection, and bleſsed and holy is he that hath part in the firſt reſurrection, on ſuch the ſecond death hath no power;</hi> for thoſe that live with Chriſt in heaven in regard of their ſouls onely, ſhall live with him eternally, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of both bodies and ſouls in the celeſtial <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> but although this explication be true in it ſelf, yet you muſt obſerve, that it is not proper in this place of Scripture, which conſiders the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and godly men not as departed from this world, but as living upon the earth; and ſo S. <hi>John</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the wicked as dead in their ſins, and having part in the firſt ſpiritual death, and the godly men
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61843:59"/>as living by grace, and having part in the firſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual reſurrection.</p>
                     <p>I could raiſe many more Arguments againſt the doctrine which the Millenaries hold concerning that Monarchical kingdom, but I will not be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: I ſhall paſs by the three ſeveral aſſenſions of Chriſt which they hold, for we know no ſuch thing in the Scripture; I ſhall alſo omit the place which ſome Millenaries maintain beſides heaven and hell, where the ſouls of them are, who ſhall riſe to reign with Chriſt a thouſand years; for you know that the Scripture makes onely mention of two places after death; the one of which ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his <hi>hypognoſt.</hi> is according to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick faith, <hi>the kingdom of heaven,</hi> and the other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame faith, ſaith this Father and Doctour of the Chriſtian Church, is <hi>hell; Etenim tertium locum penitus ignoramus;</hi> for we are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ignorant of a third place, which is confirmed in his Book <hi>de precat. merit. cap.</hi> 28. and inſinuated in the 22. <hi>artic.</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will not trouble you with the ſeveral paſſages of Scripture which they bring to prove that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchical kingdom, which they will have with Chriſt, it is enough to tell you, that they put a meerly literal conſtruction upon the Propheſies and promiſes of Scripture, which the holy Ghoſt intended to be ſpiritually underſtood; for if the Prophets ſpeak concerning the kingdom of Chriſt the re-edifying of the Jewiſh Cities, the pomp
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61843:60"/>and magnificence of reſtored <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their large priviledges, they draw thoſe things to a groſs corporal, and ſyllabical ſenſe, which the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole Chriſtian Church ſeconded by the event, hath upon good ground ever conſtrued not of the letter but of the ſpirit, to ſhew the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable condition &amp; great advantage of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Church under Chriſt, manifeſted in the fleſh; which evidently teacheth us, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Chriſt had onely two ſeveral kingdoms, of which the one is <hi>providential,</hi> and the other <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual,</hi> in which the Saints live and reign with Chriſt, as you may ſee in my Text, where S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of that kingdom, ſaith, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But for a clear illuſtration of thoſe kingdoms, you muſt obſerve, that the <hi>providential</hi> kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, is his eſſential, univerſal and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural kingdom, which he adminiſtreth as God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his creatures, in Majeſty and glory, with his Father, and the holy Ghoſt, and obtaineth as the onely Son of his Father, <hi>jure naturali,</hi> which kingdom is mentioned in <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, 4.34. and 6.26. but the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt figured by the kingdom of <hi>Judah</hi> is the donative, perſonal, and oeconomical kingdom, which the Son of God received from his Father, as you may ſee in <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.6, 8. where God having <hi>ſet his Son for our King upon his holy hill of Sion,</hi> ſaith to him, <hi>Ask of me, and I ſhall give thee the Nations
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61843:60"/>for thine inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſseſsion;</hi> as having in any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys ſome that are to be ſaved, as we ſee in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.9. where it is ſaid, that <hi>Chriſt hath redeemed us unto God by his bloud, out of every kindred, tongue, people, and nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, you may ſee the ſpiritual kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. where it is written, <hi>that in the days of the Kings of the fourth divided Kingdom,</hi> which was the Roman Empire, <hi>the God of heaven ſhall ſet up a kingdom,</hi> that is, the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>which ſhall never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,</hi> in which kingdom the Saints living a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and celeſtial life reign with Chriſt; for as you read in my Text, which ſpeaks of that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and <hi>they lived and reigned with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But for a clear intelligence you muſt obſerve, that the ſpiritual kingdom of Chriſt is diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into two wiſe, by reaſon of its two ſeveral ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations; into the kingdom of grace, and the kingdom of glory, where the kingdom of grace is the Soveraignty which Chriſt exerciſeth in this world over the Elect, governing his people by the Scepter of his holy Word, and defending them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their enemies, the devil, the fleſh, and the world, by the mighty vertue of his bleſſed Spirit, which is that kingdom which S. <hi>John</hi> in chap. 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 5. ſpeaks of, ſaying, <hi>Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God;</hi> and <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. the grand Apoſtle
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61843:61"/>ſaith, that <hi>the kingdom of God,</hi> which is, the kingdom of grace, <hi>is not meat and drink, but righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt;</hi> the kingdom of glory is that Royal Government and Empire, which Chriſt the King of kings moſt gloriouſly exerciſeth over the triumphant members of his Church after this life, and ſhall exerciſe for ever in his glorious Palace of heaven, over the bodies and ſouls of all the bleſſed of his Father, after the univerſal Reſurrection, which is that kingdom which is mentioned, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11. when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that many ſhall come from the Eaſt and Weſt, and ſhall ſit down with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>braham, Iſaac, and Jacob in the kingdom of heaven,</hi> and S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29. when he ſaith, <hi>I will not drink hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth of this fruit of the vine, until that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers kingdom.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But leaving the kingdom of glory, give me leave to tell you, that in our Text S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of the kingdom of grace when he ſaith, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt;</hi> for you may obſerve, that here is deſcribed the happy condition of the mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church all the time of the ſhutting up of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, in which the faithfull will reign with Chriſt, over the devil, the fleſh, and the world, overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their enemies in their very death and moſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el tortures, as you may obſerve by the words that precede my Text, where S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe <hi>that ſuffered for the word of God, and for the witneſs of Jeſus,;</hi> after which he addes, <hi>and they lived and reigned,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:61843:61"/>
                     <p>Moreover, the ſeditions, battels, and ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which follow that happy condition of the Church, as you may ſee in the 8. <hi>ver.</hi> where it is ſaid, that <hi>Satan after the expiration of the thouſand years, ſhall go out to deceive the nations, and gather them together to battel,</hi> evidently ſhews, that it is of the kingdom of grace which S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of; which obligeth me to ſay, <hi>and they lived,</hi> that is, the life of grace, which is mentioned in <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. where the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I live,</hi> that is, the life of grace, <hi>yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me; and the life,</hi> that is of grace, <hi>that I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God;</hi> and indeed, it is onely in that gracious kingdom of Chriſt that we live that celeſtial and ſpiritual life; for the life and kingdom of grace are inſeparable, he that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the life of grace reigneth with Chriſt, and he that reigneth with Chriſt lives the life of grace; and ſo S. <hi>John</hi> joyns them together, ſaying, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if you regard the Martyrs who died under <hi>Domitianus</hi> and other cruel Emperours, enemies of the Church of God, we may ſay, <hi>and they with the reſt of the Saints lived and reigned with Chriſt;</hi> for the bloud of the Martyrs is the ſeed of the Church, by which many come unto the ſaving knowledge of Chriſt to reign with him in his kingdom of grace, and in regard of thoſe Saints that are born of them, we reade in the 6. <hi>verſe, and they in their ſeed ſhall reign with Chriſt,</hi> where you
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61843:62"/>may obſerve, that here there is no mention of the Millenaries Monarchical kingdom, and indeed without ſuch a kingdom the Saints reign upon the Earth with Chriſt by grace, they reign with him by faith, by hope, by patience, and by all the reſt of the Chriſtian vertues; then let us ſay, <hi>and they lived and reign'd with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> which leads me to the ſecond part of my Text,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>The Second Part.</head>
                     <p>That number 1000 is taken in <hi>Scripture definite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>indefinitely; definitely</hi> for a certain &amp; limited number, as you may ſee <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.15. and 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.4. <hi>indefinitely</hi> for a great but not limited num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as you may ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.1. where a 1000. lords ſignifie a <hi>great multitude of nobility;</hi> and ſo a great but not limited number is deſigned by <hi>many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, Rev.</hi> 5.11. according to which ſence we ſhall take that number of <hi>a thouſand years</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in our Text, for S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaking of the time of Satans binding, in which the Saints ſhould reign with our Lord and Saviour with progreſs, although not without affliction, ſaith, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years,</hi> and that is confirmed by the Royal Prophet, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 90 4. where he ſaith, <hi>that a thouſand years are as yeſterday in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> and after him. S. <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. tels us, that <hi>one day is with the Lord as a thouſand years, and a thouſand years as one day,</hi> to ſhew us, that any long time whatſoever is as one day, even
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:61843:62"/>as a moment before the Lord, becauſe the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of God admits no ſucceſſion as the eternity of angels and men, for in the eternity of God no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is paſſed and nothing is to come, all things are preſent unto him, which is not to be found in the eternity of angels and ſouls of men, where there is ſucceſſion to be found, and indeed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the eternity of God from that of angels and men, which hath a beginning and no end; <hi>Boeth. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de conſol. Philoſoph.</hi> ſaith, that it is <hi>poſſeſsio totalis &amp; perfect a vitae ſine termino,</hi> a total and abſolute poſſeſſion of a life without any limit; and ſo S. <hi>Auſtin. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de ver. relig. cap.</hi> 44. ſaith, that in the eternity of God he could not perceive any interval of time, becauſe the intervals of time conſiſt in the motion of things, which are paſſed or are to come, then let me tell you, that the <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years</hi> of our Text do ſignifie all the time of the reign of the Saints, from the binding of the dragon, untill the formal manifeſtation of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-chriſtian juriſdiction, at the looſing of Satan out of his priſon; as you may ſee by the 7. and 8. <hi>verſes</hi> of our Chapter, <hi>and when the thouſand years are expired, Satan ſhall be looſed out of his priſon, and ſhall go out to deceive the nations, which are in the four quarters of the earth, Gog and Magog, to gather them together to battel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But for a clear explanation of our Text, we muſt obſerve the beginning of theſe <hi>thouſand years,</hi> for there remains the difficulty, where many Learned
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61843:63"/>men have pleaſed themſelves with their ſancies; for (leaving alone <hi>Proſper</hi> who beginneth them at the beginning of the Seventy weeks which <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet makes mention of in the ninth Chapter of his Propheſie:) Some with <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro,</hi> begin the <hi>thouſand years</hi> of our Text after the day of judgement, ſaying, that theſe thouſand years are the eternity of the Saints in majeſty and glory; but the ſeductions of the world after the looſing out of the devil, as you have ſeen in the 7. and 8. <hi>verſes</hi> of our Chapter, evidently ſhews the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: Others with the Millenaries, with <hi>Papias, Irenaeus, Tertullian, Lactantius,</hi> and others, begin them at the death of the Antichriſt; but you may obſerve, in the 7. and 8. <hi>verſes,</hi> that the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil being looſed,</hi> after the expiration of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, the Antichriſtian juriſdiction ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and ſo the thouſand years of our Text do not follow the Antichriſt but precede him: ſome of the Rabbins, <hi>Ketina</hi> and <hi>Eliezar</hi> among the Iews will have the beginning of thoſe thouſand years, after ſix thouſand of the creation of the world, at the beginning of the 7000 to the very end of it; But how do they know that the world ſhall endure neither more nor leſs then ſix thouſand years, after which the world ſhall have a reſt of a thouſand years; the Scripture I am ſure makes no mention of ſuch a thing; and therefore leaving that opinion I ſay, that others begin them at the Paſſion of our Saviour, as <hi>Gregorius</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:61843:63"/>and <hi>Pererius;</hi> but although it was ſaid, <hi>that at that time the prince of this world ſhould be caſt out,</hi> S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.31. and <hi>that in the Croſs Chriſt, having ſpoiled principalities and powers, made a ſhew of them open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, triumphing over them in it;</hi> yet you muſt know that it was not the beginning of Satans binding, and therefore I omit for the ſame reaſon the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſome Learned men that begin the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years at the <hi>death of Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, in the beginning of the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great.</p>
                     <p>For if we ſeriouſly conſider, we ſhall ſee, that a thouſand years begin at the Nativity of Jeſus Chriſt, at that time Chriſt <hi>beheld Satan as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning falling from heaven;</hi> for at his Nativity he <hi>took that ſtrong man, bound him, and ſpoiled his houſe,</hi> as Chriſt himſelf inſinuates, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.29. did not the devils know that they were bound when they beſought our Saviour ſaying, <hi>if thou caſt us out, ſuffer us to go into the herd of ſwine?</hi> Mat. 8.31. you cannot but know that verity, if you conſider that the devils could not ſtand before him without fear and trembling, as we reade in the Evangeliſts; and the heathens themſelves ſhew us, that the devils were bound at the Nativity of Jeſus Chriſt, for <hi>Suidas in vita Auguſt.</hi> recordeth, that <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> the Emperour, enquiring of the Oracle of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo,</hi> what man ſhould reign after him, received no anſwer from the devil, then that <q>an Hebrew child newly born among the Jews, hindred him
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61843:64"/>to ſpeak; and commanded him to depart from thence;</q> and I have read, that all the Images of <hi>Egypt</hi> did fall to the ground, when our bleſſed Saviour entred into that Countrey to avoid the bloudy fury of the <hi>Infanticide</hi> King <hi>Herod.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, ſome Learned Hiſtorians tell us, that the <hi>Romans</hi> having formerly conſulted the Oracles to know how long the Temple of the Goddeſs <hi>Peace</hi> ſhould ſtand, an anſwer was made them, <q>
                           <hi>until a Virgin ſhould bring forth a child;</hi>
                        </q> and ſo it came to paſs, for at the bleſſed Virgins delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it fell to the ground; and further <hi>Plutarch. de defect. orac.</hi> doth report, <q>that in the Reign of <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour, a ſtrange voice and exceeding horrible clamour, with cries and howl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, was heard by many in the <hi>Grecian</hi> Sea, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting and complaining that their great god <hi>Pan,</hi> the maſter devil was now departed, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that all the Sea reſounded their dreadfull Ecchoes;</q> whereby it is plain and manifeſt, that even in all parts the devil complained on the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of our Lord and Saviour, as being at that time ſo bound, that he could not as he did before ſeduce the Nations of the earth, for many of the Gentiles ſeduced before by him, came at that time unto the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and ſuffered Martyrdom for our Lord.</p>
                     <p>And all that agrees very well with the narration of S. <hi>John</hi> deſcribed in our Chapter, for the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Diſciple of Chriſt ſaith at the 1. <hi>verſe,</hi> that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61843:64"/>
                        <hi>he ſaw an angel coming down from heaven, having the key of the bottomleſs pit, and a great chain in his hand, to bind the prince of darkneſs with it,</hi> which ſhews us Chriſt who came down from heaven, as S. <hi>John</hi> himſelf ſaith in the 6. chap. of his Goſpel, that being conceived by the holy Ghoſt in the womb of the bleſſed Virgin, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> he might be born of her to deſtroy the works of the devil, and binde that ſtrong man, as you may reade in the 12. of S. <hi>Mat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then you may ſee that the thouſand years of our Text begin at the birth or Nativity of our Saviour, to continue untill the formal manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Antichriſtian Juriſdiction at the looſing of Satan, as you have ſeen by the 7. and 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> of our chapt. which time is already expired and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; if you conſider who are thoſe that are called <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> who are to exerciſe their tyranny againſt the Church of God, after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of the thouſand years, as you may ſee in the 8. and 9. <hi>verſes, the devil ſhall go to deceive the nations of the earth, Gog and Magog, and gather them together, and they went upon the breadth of the earth, and compaſſed the camp of the Saints about, and the beloved City.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You know that <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> are two words which are taken from the 38. of <hi>Ezechiel</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, where the Jews by <hi>Gog</hi> underſtand the <hi>king,</hi> and by <hi>Magog</hi> the <hi>people;</hi> but you are not ignorant that <hi>Magog</hi> was one of the Sons of <hi>Japheth,</hi> as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:61843:65"/>reade in <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.2. who at the firſt did inhabit next to the <hi>Caſpian</hi> mountains, and by ſucceſſion of time extended themſelves into all parts of the world; from thence came the <hi>Scythians, Tartari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and other <hi>Barbarians,</hi> from thence came the <hi>Hunnians, Vandals</hi> and <hi>Goths,</hi> and therefore it is not without reaſon, that thoſe people are ſaid to be <hi>as the ſand of the ſea</hi> in the latter end of the 8. <hi>ver.</hi> of our chapt. for they have ſupplied the world with almoſt an infinite number of people, which cauſed ſome Learned men to ſay, that the North was the ſhop of all Nations, from thence come alſo <hi>Turks,</hi> who by violence took away the <hi>Saracenical</hi> Empire; as for <hi>Gog</hi> you know that it is the proper name of one of <hi>Joels</hi> ſons of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of <hi>Reuben,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.4. who inhabited Eaſtward, and filled the Little <hi>Aſia</hi> with his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, which was called <hi>Gog.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But theſe Nations which came from <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> having degenerated from their anceſtours, became cruel enemies unto the people of God, as you ſee by <hi>Ezech.</hi> 38. and from thence the Scripture ſpeaks of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> to repreſent the open and ſecret enemies of the Chriſtian Church, as you ſee by the 8. <hi>ver.</hi> of our Chapter, with a part of the 9. <hi>ver.</hi> which ſhews us, that thoſe Nations <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog compaſſed about the Camp of the Saints</hi> to ſight them, then we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but underſtand the <hi>Turks</hi> by <hi>Magog,</hi> and the Pontificial Tyranny with the cruelty of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61843:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>by <hi>Gog;</hi> as for <hi>Magog</hi> from <hi>Miggag reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>diſcovered</hi> it becomes well the <hi>Turks,</hi> for they are manifeſt enemies of Jeſus Chriſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen perſecutours of his poor members; they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly eſteem <hi>Mahomet</hi> that grand Impoſtour, the ſon of the Prince of darkneſs, before our Lord and Saviour, who is the Son of God, and prefer their <hi>Alcoran</hi> full of <hi>Gentiliſm, Judaiſm,</hi> and <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> compiled by men of impiety, before the ſacred Scripture, inſpired by the holy Ghoſt the eſſential piety; as for <hi>Gog,</hi> let me tell you that it becomes well the tyranny of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the cruelty of the Sectaries; for <hi>Gog</hi> from <hi>Gag</hi> is the ſame as <hi>covered</hi> and <hi>hidden,</hi> which is very fit for them, for they cover and hide their tyranny and cruelty under the cloak of Religion, profeſſing <hi>one Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified,</hi> when they crucifie and hand the true members of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; in all their wicked deſignes they pretend the good of the Church, when they rend and defile it; and ſo by a damnable hypocriſie cover all their profanations and wickedneſſes, as you have in this Realm beheld with your eyes; where the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites with the Sectaries erected a black Tribunal for a moſt pious and Chriſtian King, and his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects, under a pretext of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                     <p>And indeed as <hi>Gog</hi> did degenerate from his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſour <hi>Jacob,</hi> and his father <hi>Joel,</hi> who with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility and reverence adored the Almighty God
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:61843:66"/>of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and followed his orders, ſo did the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the Sectaries degenerate from their Anceſtours, who acknowledged with all humility and obedience the Church of God and its orders; or if you will, as <hi>Gog</hi> did imitate <hi>Reuben</hi> who defiled his fathers bed, ſo the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with the Sectaries imitate Satan, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth the Church of God with Schiſmes and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; which makes you clearly ſee, that <hi>the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is looſed out of his priſon,</hi> and that <hi>the thouſand years are expired and finiſhed; they lived and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Chriſt a thouſand years;</hi> not that I will ſay that the Saints do not now reign with Chriſt, for I know that they do reign with him when they are his regenerated Subjects, but that now they reign not with Chriſt with ſuch progreſs as they did before the expiration of the thouſand years of Satans binding; for we ſeldom now ſee a true converſion, or a ſincere repentance of our ſins, but rather often obſtination appears in our errours, we will not change them becauſe we defended our ſins openly, and ſo by our ambition we deſtroy the Church of our bleſſed Saviour; there is no fear of God amongſt us, nor ſincere love one to another, nor charity towards our poor afflicted bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as there was in the time of Satans binding; we are as hard as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as cruel as <hi>Cain,</hi> and as profane as <hi>Eſau;</hi> it ſeems that all the Chriſtian vertues are vaniſhed amongſt men, and that all vices have took their places to give way unto the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61843:66"/>prince of darkneſs, who is now looſed out of his priſon; for <hi>they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Perhaps you will tell me, if the thouſand years are now ſiniſhed, or as you ſaid, <hi>expired</hi> at the formal manifeſtation of the Antichriſtian Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, how can it be ſaid, that <hi>Satan is looſed out for a little while</hi> or <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> as it is ſpoken in the 3. <hi>ver.</hi> To that I anſwer and ſay, that this may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well be ſaid in regard of Satans eternal binding, which followeth after his looſing out of his priſon for a while; indeed if you conſider the thouſand years binding of Satan, I confeſs that his looſing out will ſeem a great while; but if you look upon Satans eternal binding, his looſing out is but <hi>a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſeaſon,</hi> which makes me wonder at the Mille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries opinion, who expect now a viſible and earthly reign, for in the expectation of ſuch a reign, they looſe the ſpiritual kingdom of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and in their pretended happineſs, they may finde a true unhappineſs.</p>
                     <p>But I will ſtay no longer upon that imaginary kingdom, for the kingdom that I propoſed unto you, is a true and ſpiritual kingdom; the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Saviour which is of grace, without which it is impoſſible to obtain the kingdom of glory; for you know, that we muſt firſt reign here in grace, before we can reign hereafter in glory; then let me tell you, that the Saints who now reign with Chriſt in glory, lived and reigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61843:67"/>with him in grace by many years; for as you read in my Text, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="text">
                     <head>Concluſion and Application.</head>
                     <p>But let us conclude with application, to learn from our Text, that the Saints who are actual members of our Saviour live with him in this world the life of grace, the onely life of Gods children, who are not <hi>born of the fleſh but of the Spirit,</hi> Joh. 3.6. <hi>not of corruptible but incorruptible ſeed, the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. not of the prince of darkneſs, but of the Father of lights; for as we read, <hi>and they lived and reigned with Chriſt;</hi> indeed there is none but thoſe that are light in the Lord that poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs it; for this ſpiritual life changes our darkneſs into light, and our vices into ſhining vertues, and makes us like unto the Sun of righteouſneſs by the gracious brightneſs which the life of grace procures unto us, which is a life that the Scripture cals the <hi>life of Chriſt;</hi> becauſe the life of grace looks on Chriſt as on its ſacred object, and its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious cauſe; and by excellency the <hi>life of God,</hi> not as if God were not the authour of the natural life of the vegetative, ſenſitive, reaſonable, and intelligent creatures, for we know that the God of heaven and earth gives life to all theſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and that the natural life dependeth of him as of the God of nature; but it is ſo called becauſe God by the life of his grace liveth in his children,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61843:67"/>that they may live unto him, and conform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to his ſacred Will; for the regenerated know that by that life <hi>we die to ſin, and live to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, always tending towards the mark for the price of the high calling of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, the life of grace is ſuch an advantage to the regenerated Chriſtian, that by it the image of our God, which we by our ſins have deſiled, is reſtored in our corrupted nature, and therefore the Scripture ſhews us, that the life of grace is nothing elſe but the <hi>new creature</hi> and the <hi>new man:</hi> I wiſh that I could ſpeak with the tongue of Angels to expreſs in ſome kinde that celeſtial and ſpiritual life which the Saints enjoy in our Saviour, for I am ſure that you would be raviſhed with admiration in the very hearing of that ſacred life, yet I deſire that you give place to my weakneſs, excuſe my infirmities, and ſuffer me to exhort you to run af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it with all the ſincerity of your hearts.</p>
                     <p>But before, forſake the world and its luſts; for it is impoſſible to live with Chriſt while we live the life of this corrupted world; let then every one of us pull down the Idols which we have erected upon our hearts to the profanation of the Name of the Almighty God, and confuſion of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls; you that are covetous, let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you to remove <hi>Mammon</hi> from your affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that you may offer an agreeable ſacrifice unto God, and come to the life of grace; conſider that riches continue not long with us, for you know
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61843:68"/>that ſometimes the ſea, that unconſtant Element takes by violence all ours, and that which we had from others, as great Merchants by experience may inform you, and ſometimes a ſickneſs will conſume our eſtate; nay, ſometimes the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or bad conſcience of our debitours will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of all our revenues, and make us poor and miſerable; but ſuppoſe that all your goods remain with you all your lives time, at laſt they muſt leave you although you will not leave them; for at death, you carry nothing with you but a winding-ſheet in the grave, and a good or bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before the tribunal of God:</p>
                     <p>You that are voluptuous, leave your ſenſual pleaſures that hinder you to come to the life of grace; Conſider that the pleaſures of this world paſs as ſoon as they appear unto us, you enjoy them for ſome moments onely, and that with grief after their poſſeſſion; for you know that ſorrow inſeparably follows the ſenſual pleaſures of this world; thoſe beauties which captivate our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are mortal and changeable, and vaniſh at the leaſt ſickneſs, but we are blinded by the fatal and irreligious <hi>Cupid,</hi> which holds us faſt with his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous chains, which we muſt break to turn our faces to the eternal beauty which is unchangeable and full of purity and holineſs, that we may enjoy the celeſtial pleaſures with the ſpiritual life which we have in Chriſt; you that are ambitious leave your worldly honours, and pull down your pride,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:61843:68"/>and with humility deſire of God through Jeſus Chriſt the life of grace, that you may live with our bleſſed Saviour; let every ſinner pluck his ſins out of his own heart, that he may be able to receive the celeſtial impreſſions upon it, to die unto ſin, and live unto righteouſneſs.</p>
                     <p>But obſerve, that if the Saints or faithfull live with Chriſt in this world, they reign alſo with him, for it is onely in the gracious kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt that we live the life of grace; and it is true enough, nay, no Chriſtian can deny, that the Saints reign here with Chriſt, for in his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the Saints have power over their ſinfull fleſh, when before their coming into it, the fleſh had power over them; which obliges the grand Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle S. <hi>Paul</hi> Rom. 6.12. to ſay, <hi>let not ſin reign therefore in your mortal bodies, that you ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof;</hi> in that kingdom of Chriſt we have power over the prince of darkneſs, the god of this world; for in that kingdom we have him under our feet, all that he can do is to howl and cry, but not hurt nor offend; for in all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults which the devil preſents unto the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Subjects of our Saviour in the kingdom of Chriſt, they obtain the victory through him who ſuffered for their ſins, and deſtroyed for them that power which Satan had over them; in that kingdom of our Lord we have alſo power over this corrupted world, when before, it had an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over us; you are no more ſubjects nor ſlaves
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61843:69"/>of its corruptible treaſures, vaniſhing honours, and ſenſual pleaſures; for if you poſſeſs ſome honours, enjoy ſome pleaſures, and have riches, you apply not your hearts unto them, and ſo you poſſeſs them as poſſeſſing them not.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, Conſider what advantage we have in that ſpiritual kingdom of Chriſt; for reigning with him we are in ſome kinde <hi>mundi Domim,</hi> the Lords of the world, becauſe we have a ſpiritual right to all the creatures of God; for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. <hi>all things are yours;</hi> but I ſay a ſpiritual right to diſtinguiſh it from that which we call natural and civil right, which men have to that which they legally poſſeſs, for we muſt take heed of this errour which makes an u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall confuſion whereever it prevaileth.</p>
                     <p>Now give me leave to tell you, that it is by faith that we here reign with Chriſt, and that it is by hope, by charity, and by patience with all the reſt of the Chriſtian vertues; for you know that they defend and hold us faſt againſt our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, ſo that we prevail againſt them in our afflictions and calamities even in our death; Leave then the Millenaries with the earthly opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their worldly kingdom; let them poſſeſs the earth if they will, as for us we muſt look up to heaven to give there all our meditations while we live upon the earth; we muſt leave the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kingdoms to the <hi>Alexanders</hi> and <hi>Gaeſars,</hi> and ſeek after the ſpiritual kingdom of Chriſt, for it
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61843:69"/>is impoſſible to come into the Celeſtial Palace of our God, if we have not been in the gracious king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Saviour; then let us all look now for that kingdom, and keep there all our life time, that having lived and reigned with Chriſt in grace, we may hereafter live and reign with him in glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:70"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:70"/>
                  <head>To the truly Noble and Religious Gentlewoman, M.<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
                     <hi>TAMISEN BROOK Grace, Happineſs and Peace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I were ignorant of your great Piety and Charity, many hundred Families would make me know it; you and your moſt worthy Family is always at work for the poor members of our bleſſed Saviour; you are another <hi>Dorcas, full of good works,</hi> your thoughts are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in heaven though you live upon the earth, your words tend continually to union and peace, and your great care is to <hi>work out your ſalvation with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling;</hi> which is ſeen not onely in your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb facs="tcp:61843:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>devotions, but in the publick ones, where I may ſay that you are a pious and godly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to all others of your Sex; indeed the Church of <hi>England,</hi> among all the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhe did procreate, there are few to be compared with you; but if your humility will not accept of that expreſsion, permit me to make all the Engliſh world know that the Church never poſſeſsed a better one; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one knows that your houſe is a Temple, and a little Church where Vows and Prayers are continually ſent up to heaven for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Church of <hi>England</hi> our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for our gracious Prince, nay, for the converſion of thoſe that are diſtant from the true knowledge of our Saviour, who came into the world to redeem us from our iniquities, the redemption of men being our Saviours meat, which I preſent you with as it was delivered by me in a Sermon, which I hope you will accept, being the meat which daily you and your worthy Family feed upon;
<pb facs="tcp:61843:71"/>for I am not ignorant, that it is your ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar pleaſure and delectation; nay, I am ſure that it is ſo agreeable unto you, that you will kindely receive it from him, who is,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your moſt humble and obedient Servant, James Le Franc.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:61843:72"/>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:61843:72"/>
                  <head>Chriſts Spiritual Meat: <hi>Delivered in a Sermon Preached in Engliſh at the French Church in</hi> Norwich.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>S. JOH. 4.34.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is common amongſt men to extoll the perſons of merit and reputation, but if any amongſt you hath ever e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed a learned and moſt prudent wit, that could upon any matter chooſe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations fit for the inſtruction of his auditours, and by the object of the ſight and other external ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, could with a marvellous induſtry and aptneſs awake the internal ſenſes, and lift up our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings to the contemplation of the higheſt things, let him now reflect upon our Maſter, the eternal Wiſedom of God the Father our great do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, Chriſt <hi>who is over all God bleſſed for ever;</hi> let him ſay with me that there is none, that ought to be parallel'd with him; for if you conſider the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:61843:73"/>induſtry which Chriſt our Mediatour uſed when he was living upon the earth, you will eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that it was admirable, for he ever made uſe of his Celeſtial Induſtry to promote his Fathers glory and mens ſalvation, taking ſometimes an occaſion from their too great inclination which they had after the things of this world, to draw them into the knowledge and inquiſition of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and eternal things of the heavenly <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> as you may obſerve in the 6. Chapt. of S. <hi>John;</hi> where Chriſt ſeeing the people carefull to ſeek after him for onely corruptible and common meat, took occaſion to diſcourſe with them about the ſacred bread of God, and the ſpiritual manna, which <hi>if any man eat of, he ſhall live for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now let us follow Chriſt through <hi>Samaria,</hi> to obſerve ſome things of his celeſtial actions and wonderfull works; but ſeeing that Chriſt doth ſtay, let us ſtay with him, for I perceive that our Saviour is weary of his journey, and forced to reſt himſelf on <hi>Jacobs</hi> well, but while he reſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, there cometh a woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> to draw water; Chriſt diſcourſeth with her about the true and ſpiritual worſhip of God, and takes occaſion from the water to inſtruct her about the celeſtial fountain of living water, which ſhe taſted of with ſuch pleaſure, that ſhe, leaving her waterpot, went into the City to call her fellow-Citizens, the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans,</hi> and invite them to the participation of that ſpiritual water which ſhe had received from
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:61843:73"/>our bleſſed Saviour: But while ſhe thus runs to invite them, the diſciples of our Lord deſire him to eat, but Chriſt whoſe hunger was after the ſouls of men, ſaid unto them, <hi>I have meat to eat that ye know not of,</hi> which made them beleeve that while they were abſent ſome body had brought him ſomething to eat, ſaying one to another, <hi>hath any man brought him ought to eat?</hi> but Chriſt that he might no longer keep them in ſuſpence, <hi>becauſe it was given unto them to know the myſteries of the kingdom of heaven,</hi> teaches them, with ſew but ſignificant words, a great and ſublime myſtery, ſaying, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work,</hi> which are the words which I have choſen to entertain you with by the ſpecial aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt; but for a clear intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of them, I ſhall divide my Text into two parts, where in the firſt I ſhall entertain you with the will and work of him that ſent Chriſt, and in the ſecond part I ſhall ſhew you, that that will and work of God is our Saviours meat, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>The firſt Part.</head>
                     <p>As the Philoſophers place the moral vertues in two ranks, where in the firſt the vertues are glorious and worthy to be loved of themſelves, as <hi>Juſtice;</hi> and in the ſecond rank, worthy to be wiſhed for the vertues of the firſt, as <hi>Courage</hi> which is a ſit vertue, when juſtice ceaſeth amongſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:61843:74"/>men; ſo the Schoolmen divide the attributes of God into two orders, where in the firſt the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes are incommunicable unto the creatures; as Gods Immenſity, Independency, and Unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, for all the creatures of the Univerſe, even the Angels, are dependent, changeable and limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted natures; but the attributes of the ſecond or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der are ſaid to be proportionably communicable, <hi>in effectis analogis,</hi> by the reſemblance of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as Gods Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Will, for you know that thoſe attributes are aſcribed unto Angels, and given unto men; and as God hath a will, ſo have Angels and men, as being the right of the intelligent creatures.</p>
                     <p>But here we ſhall not ſpeak of Angels nor mens will, but of Gods will, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me;</hi> for he that ſent Chriſt is God the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old Maxim of Divinity, <hi>opera Dei ad extra ſunt indiviſa, ſeu toti Trinitati Communia,</hi> the outward operations of God are common to the whole Trinity; ſo that you muſt obſerve that the Son, the ſecond Perſon of the bleſſed Trinity, was ſent as Mediatour; for he was one of thoſe bleſſed Perſons who did conſult about mens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, nay, more then that, he was that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred one, who of his own free-will offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be conſecrated for the performance of that gracious work, as you may ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5, 6, 7. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice and offering thou wouldeſt not, but a body haſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:61843:74"/>thou prepared me, in burnt-offerings and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for ſin thou haſt had no pleaſure, then ſaid I, lo, I come to do thy will;</hi> where you may eaſily obſerve, that Chriſt as God ſent himſelf as Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour, that he might redeem us from the power of the Prince of darkneſs, and the ſpiritual bondage of our ſins.</p>
                     <p>Nevertheleſs becauſe the firſt Perſon of the bleſſed Trinity is the Father of our Mediatour, and the Perſon <hi>a quo filius agit,</hi> from which the Son doth act; the ſending of Chriſt into the world for our ſalvation, is particularly attributed unto him, as you may ſee in the 5. Chapter of S. <hi>John,</hi> 36. <hi>ver. the ſame works that I do, bear witneſs of me, that the Father hath ſent me,</hi> which verily is aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in many other places of that Goſpel; and ſo in that ſence we muſt ſay, <hi>my meat is to do the will of him that ſent me,</hi> for indeed you muſt obſerve, that that perſon amongſt theſe of the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity who ſends another, is that perſon from which the perſon ſent proceeds, and ſo we reade in the Scripture, that the <hi>Father hath ſent his Son,</hi> and the Son <hi>miſit Spiritum à Patre,</hi> did ſend the holy Ghoſt from the Father, but we do not reade, that the Son hath ſent the Father, nor the holy Ghoſt the Son, becauſe the Father proceeds not from the Son, nor the Son from the holy Ghoſt, but the Son is from the Father alone, and the holy Ghoſt proceeds from the Father and Son; then let us ſay as before, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:61843:75"/>that ſent me:</hi> And indeed you muſt conſider, that the Father is Authour of our ſalvation by a way which is not given to the Son our Mediatour, as the Son our Mediatour is Authour of our ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a way which is not given to the Father; for as the Learned men diſtinguiſh ſome eſſential o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations of the bleſſed Trinity, <hi>reſpectu termini,</hi> and make them perſonal operations, as the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Father, the Redemption to the Son, and the Sanctification to the holy Ghoſt; ſo they divide the waies by which the Perſons of the bleſſed Trinity are ſaid to be Authours of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; for the firſt Perſon of the Bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is the Father, is ſaid to be the authour of our ſalvation by way of procuration, becauſe he procured us that great work in the ſending of his Son, and ſo Chriſt ſaith, <hi>my meat is to do the will of him that ſent me;</hi> the Son our Mediatour is authour of our ſalvation by way of merit, becauſe the Son of God alone is the meritorious cauſe of our ſalvation, not the Father, for he alone ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired it for us through his bloud; the holy Ghoſt is ſaid to be authour of our ſalvation by way of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, becauſe the holy Ghoſt our Sanctifier applieth unto our ſouls the great benefit of our Redemption by his divine vertue.</p>
                     <p>Now you muſt obſerve in our Text the Father to be authour of our Salvation by way of procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and the Son by way of merit, for in my Text, the Father ſends the Son, and the Son our
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:61843:75"/>Mediatour finiſheth the work and executeth his Fathers will, for Chriſt ſpeaking as Mediatour ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>But let us come to the explication of Gods will, and give me leave to ſay with ſome Learned men for our illuſtration, that there are three ſorts of wills attributed unto God, <hi>reſpectu rerum quas Deus vult extra ſeipſum,</hi> in regard of things which God wills out of himſelf; I ſay in regard of things which God wills out of himſelf, for if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the object of Gods will, as not being out of himſelf, you muſt know, that the object of his will is God himſelf, and by conſequence there is no difference in Gods will, for it is nothing elſe but <hi>Deus ſcipſum volens.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In regard then of things that God wills out of himſelf, the firſt ſort of will attributed unto God, and that properly is <hi>voluntas decreti,</hi> the will of Gods Decrees, by which he freely and moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly from all eternity determined to manifeſt all things which were to be framed in time, of which will it is ſpoken in the 1. Chapt. to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the 9. <hi>ver.</hi> when the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that God hath made known unto us the myſtery of his will,</hi> that is, the will of Gods decree, which by the Schoolmen is called <hi>voluntas beneplaciti,</hi> the will of Gods good pleaſure, becauſe by it, according to his good pleaſure, and without any merit in our ſelves he loved us; <hi>voluntas antecedens</hi> Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:61843:76"/>will, becauſe from all eternity, before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing was created, it was approved in God; <hi>voluntas abſoluta,</hi> Gods abſolute will, becauſe it is grounded upon his good pleaſure, and doth not depend of things which are framed in time; and <hi>voluntas occulta</hi> Gods ſecret will, becauſe a <hi>a priori</hi> at the firſt, it was not revealed unto the ſacred Angels, nor perceived by men;</p>
                     <p>The ſecond ſort of will aſcribed unto God, and that improperly, is <hi>voluntas ſigni,</hi> Gods will of ſigne, by which God ſhews us what is agreeable unto him, and what he will have us to do; which is the mark and teſtimony of Gods decree mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in his holy word, although not always the ſigne of that decree which is firſt conceived by us; which will, indued with ſeveral names, as Gods conditional will, Gods revealed will, and Gods conſequent will, is declared unto us under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a commandment or prohibition, and under the rule of a promiſe or threatning; for as the Magiſtrates Commands are called their will, ſo Gods Commandments or Promiſes are called his will, as you may ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 13.22. <hi>I have found David the Son of Jeſſe a man after mine own heart, which ſhall fulfill all my will,</hi> or as it is expreſſed in the Original, in regard of ſeveral Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Orders, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>all my wills.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The third and laſt ſort of will attributed unto is <hi>voluntas objecti,</hi> Gods will of object, which is
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:61843:76"/>nothing elſe but the things that God wills, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and preſcribes unto us; that is the object of Gods Commandments, as it doth appear, 1 <hi>The.</hi> 4.3. <hi>this is the will of God, even your ſanctification,</hi> ſo in the Lords Prayer when we ſay <hi>thy will be done;</hi> and in our Text, Chriſt ſpeaking of that will of object, ſaith, <hi>my meat is to do the will of him that ſent me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now to know what is meant by that will, we cannot have a better Interpreter then Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who ſaith in the 6. Chapter of S. <hi>John, ver.</hi> 39. <hi>This is the Fathers will which hath ſent me, that of all which he hath given me, I ſhould loſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up again at the laſt day;</hi> it was that which his Father told him before his Incarnation <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6, 7. <hi>I the Lord have called thee in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to open the blinde eyes, to bring out the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from the priſon, and them that ſit in darkneſs out of the priſon houſe;</hi> and you know when Chriſt prepared himſelf for the execution of his Fathers will, that he ſaid, <hi>Lo, I come to do thy will,</hi> Heb. 10.9. <hi>by which will,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>ver</hi> 10. <hi>we are ſanctified through the offering of the body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But for a clearer illuſtration, let me tell you, that this will is the ſalvation of man, which our Lord came to advance and to accompliſh, for you know that to that end Chriſt was ſent into the world, <hi>that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh but have everlaſting life,</hi> Joh. 3.16. a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:61843:77"/>truth which manifeſtly appears, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.6. when he ſaith in the perſon of the Father, ſpeaking to the Son, <hi>I will give thee for a light unto the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that thou mayeſt be my ſalvation unto the end of the earth;</hi> nay, a truth manifeſted by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our when he lived amongſt us, as now he will have us to underſtand it, when he ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work;</hi> then you may obſerve, that this will of God was the manifeſtation of his Fathers moſt ſacred counſel unto the world, Chriſt being the ſacred Interpreter of his Father, and the word by which he informs us of his will, for as Chriſt ſaith, S. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.27. <hi>all things are delivered unto me of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no man knoweth the Son but the Father; neither knoweth any man the Father but the Son, and be to whom the Son will reveal him,</hi> this ſacred will of God was the ſulfilling of the Law for thoſe who ſhould receive him by a moſt ſiducial apprehenſion, for as <hi>Ambroſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>perſectionem legis habet qui credit in Chriſtum,</hi> he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in Chriſt hath the perfection of the Law, which he had learned from the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom 10.4. who ſays Chriſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> the <hi>end or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Law for righteouſneſs to every one that beleeveth;</hi> this ſacred will of God was the death of our Saviour for the ſins of thoſe that ſhould obey him, as you clearly ſee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. where we reade, <hi>that Chriſt being made perfect through ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, he became the authour of eternal ſalvation unto
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:61843:77"/>all them that obey him, that they may be conformed to the moſt bright image of him that ſaith, My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me,</hi> but let us adde, <hi>and to ſiniſh his work.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To tell you that, I need not to give you an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeration of all Gods works, for the work of God, of which it is ſpoken in our Text, is the ſame as the will of him that ſent Chriſt; for as <hi>Euthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> ſaith, the will of the Father who ſent Chriſt, and the work committed unto him, is the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, according to that of S. <hi>John,</hi> 17.4. where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I have ſiniſhed the work which thou gaveſt me to do,</hi> and ſo the will of God which we have expounded unto you, is the work of God which our Saviour had to perform, and indeed it is not without cauſe, that this will is called <hi>a work</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſatisfaction for mens ſins, and their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God is a work by excellency, a work compounded of many works, which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs are under one work, which is our redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption; then you muſt obſerve that this work doth not conſiſt in the laſt act that Chriſt performed upon the Croſs; for he wrought in it when he <hi>ſought after the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> he wrought in that gracious work when he lett the Gentiles, their neighbours, take ſome crumbs of his ſacred bread for the ſalvation of their ſouls; he wrought in it when he did communicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unto the <hi>Samaritans</hi> which were grown a baſe people, and amongſt whom the ſervice of the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:61843:78"/>God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not pure, he wrought in that ſacred work all the time he was upon the earth, till his obedience was accompliſhed upon the Croſs, where he ſaid, <hi>It is ſiniſhed,</hi> S. John 19.30. <hi>ver.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But obſerve, that this work is of another rank then that of our good works which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, approveth and worketh in us by his holy Spirit; for this work of our ſalvation is the great and ſublime work of God; a work which excels the great work of the Creation, be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a work, as I may ſay of greater labour then that of the Creation, for as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes, <hi>Deus loquendo creavit ſed patiendo redemit,</hi> God created the world by his ſpeaking, but he redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it by his ſuffering; becauſe the ruine and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of men was ſuch, that there were more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles at the redeeming of men, then at the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Univerſe; for, beſides there was the ſame vertue required to raiſe the dead, as to give being to nothing, and life to duſt; the juſtice of the living God was oppoſed unto their ſalvation; therefore to ſatisfie the divine juſtice the death of our dear Saviour was neceſſary for them, to whom God had ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>In the day thou eateſt of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil, thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover this work of our ſalvation is a work in which God manifeſted his Wiſedom in an higher degree then he did in that of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:61843:78"/>for beſides we know more of the Divinity by the work of our redemption, then we do by the work of the Creation (the myſtery of the Trinity being revealed unto us by that work of his grace, which was not not diſcovered by the works of nature) we ſee in our Redemption Gods admirable work; a moſt wonderfull way, where God puniſheth our ſins, and with all ſaves men by it, ſo that the puniſhment of mens ſins in our Saviour becomes the ſalvation of them; nay, more then that, in that ſacred work, Chriſt the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian took Phyſick for us his Patients, to heal us of our ſpiritual ſickneſſes, where in nature the Phyſician gives Phyſick to his Patients to cure them of their corporal diſeaſes; then let us ſay, <hi>My meat is to to do the will of him that ſent me, and to ſiniſh his work;</hi> where you muſt yet obſerve that this work is the onely work of Chriſt, for this work is ſuch, that no man nor angel can reach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, there is none but the <hi>Lion of the Tribe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> the Son of God, that can ſay in regard of this great and mighty work of our Redemption; <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his work,</hi> which leades me to the ſecond part of my Text.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:61843:79"/>
                     <head>The Second Part.</head>
                     <p>Thoſe that are acquainted with the Scripture know there are two ſorts of meat, the one for the body, which is the common ſignification, as it is the common meat; the other for the ſouls which is ſpiritual by reſemblance and proportion to the corporal meat, which is the metaphorical ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that word <hi>meat;</hi> and indeed as the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial meat maintains and keeps our bodies, ſo are our ſouls maintained and kept by the ſpiritual meat; moreover, as our bodies increaſe and receive their ſtrength againſt weakneſs, from the material meat, ſo have our ſouls their growing unto a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man in our Saviour, and receive their ſtrength againſt all temptations by the ſpiritual meat.</p>
                     <p>But if the ſpiritual meat hath ſome reſemblance with the corporal meat, give me leave to tell you, that there is ſomething in the ſpiritual meat which is not to be found in the corporal; for the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral meat muſt be given to thoſe that enjoy a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral life, otherwiſe it cannot help all our dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but the ſpiritual meat which is the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our ſouls, that proceeds from God, when it is given to thoſe that are ſpiritually dead, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores them unto a celeſtial and ſpiritual life; moreover, the corporal meat can for a time keep our natural and temporal life, but it cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from death; but the incorruptible meat of the Word of God, and above all the living bread which cometh down from heaven gives an
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:61843:79"/>everlaſting life to our ſouls, and preſerves them from eternal death.</p>
                     <p>And further you muſt obſerve; that after this life, all corporall nouriſhments ſhall ceaſe, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſpiritual nouriſhment of our ſouls for the bleſſed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> God the Father, ſhall ever ſit at the table of their maſter, to eat with him of the ſacred bread of God, and drink the new wine of the kingdom of heaven with him, that ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to ſiniſh his work,</hi> where by theſe words you may eaſily ſee, that in this place the word <hi>meat</hi> is taken in a ſpiritual ſence; but</p>
                     <p>For the better explication of this <hi>meat,</hi> let us obſerve that the ſpiritual meat hath ſome proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and effects that preſuppoſe ſome imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in our ſouls, when the ſpiritual meat is an ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and medicine for them; which cannot agree with our bleſſed Saviour, nay, more then that, thoſe qualities ought not to be aſcribed or adapt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him, who is all perfect, <hi>Chriſt our Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, who is a lamb without blemiſh and without ſpot;</hi> and you will confeſs that Chriſt who gives life to the world, needs not its entertainment nor reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any ſtrength; but behold there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the ſpiritual meat which will very well agree with our bleſſed Saviour: delectation and pleaſure, for you muſt know that as the material and corporal meat (when it is preſent and taken by a man of a good appetite) doth recreate and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:61843:80"/>generate pleaſure and delectation; and (if it be abſent) cauſeth a great deſire, ſo doth the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual meat; for when it is preſent and taken by our ſouls that ſeek after it, it recreates them, and gives the ſouls a great but ſpiritual pleaſure and delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>And after this manner the eating and drinking is taken often in the Scripture for the poſſeſſion and enjoying of very acceptable and pleaſant things; for the celeſtial and ſpiritual pleaſures which we in this life and after it ſhall enjoy in the Lord; as you may ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10. where the Pſalmiſt ſpeaking of Gods Commandments cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brates them <hi>as more to be deſired then gold, and ſweeter then honey,</hi> and in many other places of the ſame book, as <hi>Pſa.</hi> 42.3. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63.1, 5. the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prophet expreſſeth his moſt fervent deſires for God by hunger and thirſt; and his greater plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures by the fulneſs of marrow and fatneſs, ſaying, <hi>My ſoul thirſteth for God, for the living God;</hi> and then with delectation, <hi>My ſoul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs, and my mouth ſhall praiſe thee with joyfull lips;</hi> moreover, Chriſt ſpeaking unto his Diſciples of the ſacred pleaſures which we ſhall enjoy in the poſſeſſion of the ſpiritual bleſſings in the Celeſtial <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.30. <hi>I appoint unto you a kingdom that ye may eat and drink at my table.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In this ſence Chriſt calls his Fathers will and work his <hi>meat,</hi> ſaying, <hi>My meat is to do the will of
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:61843:80"/>him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work;</hi> becauſe it was all his pleaſure, all his delight, and all his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; as if Chriſt ſhould ſay unto his Diſciples, who preſented him meat that he might eat of; I am not touched now with an appetite to corporal meat, even after my wearineſs, which forces me to reſt my ſelf on <hi>Jacobs</hi> well, as I am deſirous to accompliſh Gods work, and the will of him that ſent me, and indeed the care of that great and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime work, makes me forget to eat any thing for the refection of my body; where you muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that there are two things which make men forget to eat and drink, a great ſadneſs, and a great pleaſure; for you know that ſometimes a great ſadneſs will ſo feed an afflicted man that he will forget himſelf, and leave his meat and drink, as it doth appear by our royal but afflicted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 102.4. ſaying; <hi>My heart is ſmitten, and withered like graſs, ſo that I forget to eat my bread,</hi> and <hi>Pſa.</hi> 42.3. he ſaith, <hi>My tears have been my meat day and night, while they continually ſay unto me, where is thy God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But if ſadneſs makes us forget our meat and drink, much more doth pleaſure, on which a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is framed, where it is ſaid, <hi>he takes there ſo much pleaſure that he loſeth his meat and drink;</hi> and you know that to be true, for oftentimes a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found meditation on ſome agreeable things, or a pleaſant exerciſe will make us forget the time of our refection, as it appears in our bleſſed Saviour,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:61843:81"/>who ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work;</hi> for Chriſt refuſeth the meat which his Diſciples preſented him, becauſe all his pleaſure and his delight was in the ſalvation of men, and converſion of thoſe who were to come to meet him, as you may ſee in the 40. <hi>verſe</hi> of our Chapter; he would not then feed upon his Diſciples corporal meat, but upon the converſion of men, his ſpiritual meat and delicious ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</p>
                     <p>I know that our Saviour did eat many times to ſhew the truth of his humane nature, and make the Jews and others know that he was a true man, but he did leave his meat, when neceſſity of mens ſalvation did require it, to manifeſt himſelf the Saviour of the world; indeed he uſed the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral meat with the common, but the ſalvation of men was his proper meat; for you know that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all the proviſions which God gives us for our nouriſhment, ſome there are which we taſte of with greater pleaſure then others, as you may ſee in <hi>Iſaac</hi> whoſe ſingular meat was veniſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.3. and ſo every one ſaith, ſpeaking of the meat which he ſingularly loves, <hi>this is my meat,</hi> as Chriſt in this place ſpeaking of the meat which he loved above all, ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work;</hi> Indeed being queſtion of mens ſalvation, he had a ſingular rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſay, that it was his meat, becauſe no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels nor men could deliver us from the hands of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:61843:81"/>the prince of darkneſs; none but God manifeſted in the fleſh; for Chriſt alone God manifeſted in the fleſh is the onely King who did eat at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of mens redemption; Chriſt is he alone <hi>who hath troden the wine-preſs,</hi> Iſa. 63.3. <hi>I have troden</hi> (ſaith our Saviour, ſpeaking of that he was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to perform) <hi>the winepreſs alone, and of the people there was none with me,</hi> Chriſt is he alone who hath been conſecrated by afflictions for our ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>For Chriſt being conſecrated through ſufferings, became the authour of eternal ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation unto all thoſe that obey him, and there is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther name under heaven given amongſt men where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaved but this of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Concluſion and Application.</head>
                     <p>Now brethren to conclude, let us conſider the great work of our Redemption, which our Lord and Saviour performed, from the birth of his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred perſon to his death upon the Croſs, where he ſaith, <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> that we may abſtain from ſin, and run after righteouſneſs; let us look upon the divine wiſedom that found a way to puniſh our ſins, and with all ſave men by it; nay, more then that, a way where the Phyſician took Phyſick for his Patient, to cure him of all his ſpiritual diſeaſes, that we may never ceaſe to praiſe the Lord our God whom we adore; ler us admire here the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:61843:82" rendition="simple:additions"/>affection of our dear Saviour, who being of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended as well as his Father notwithſtanding the reconciliation of men with their God and him through his bloud, that we may exclaim with the Apoſtle, that <hi>neither death, nor life, nor angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate us from the love of God which is in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, let us conſider in the work of our Redemption the union of heaven and earth, which our ſins had broke; and you ſhall ſee that the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred angels deſcend from heaven to protect, help, and comfort us againſt our enemies and eminent dangers, which beſet us in this corrupted world; being now <hi>miniſtring ſpirits, for them who ſhall be heirs of ſalvation,</hi> Heb. 1.14.</p>
                     <p>But to admire yet more the great benefits of the incomparable work of our Redemption; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeriouſly what we were by our ſins before the decretal reſolution of God to ſave men by Chriſt; examine what we are now by nature, the ſlaves of the Prince of darkneſs, the ſons of this corrupted world, and the children of death and eternal da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnation, our condition was (as it is by nature) worſe then <hi>Lots</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> then <hi>Iſraels</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> then <hi>Sampſons</hi> among the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> then the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Prophets and Apoſtles in the obſcure priſons; for we were under the power of the god of this wotld, bound with chains of obſcurity, and tyed faſt to the infernal pillory
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:61843:82"/>for our eternal ſhame, if <hi>Chriſt had not come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, let us learn here, that although Chriſt is alone in this great work of our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, yet in the general enterpriſe of doing the will of God every one according to his condition is ſent from him to do his will; Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have their work from God to do, for as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>the Princes are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God for good;</hi> they muſt kiſs the eternal Son of God, the Lord of lords, and King of kings; they muſt lay down at his feet their Sceptre and Diadem, that their kingdoms may continue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger under them; nay more then that, they muſt adminiſter all things for his glory, all the kings of the world being under Chriſt the King of kings; which the great Monarch of <hi>England</hi> moſt piouſly acknowledgeth by the Church, when ſhe ſaith, <hi>that his Majeſty is next and immediately under God and his Chriſt, in his Dominions, ſupreme Governour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſubordinate Magiſtrates have alſo their work from God to perform, they ought to do all things according to equity, and miniſter juſtice without partiality, and weigh with deliberation the conſiderable matters which they have in hand; leſt too much raſhneſs in the execution of them, ſhould embroyl them and the people with ruine and confuſion, or ſome other fatal accidents:</p>
                     <p>All the Spiritual Guides and Eccleſiaſtical Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:61843:83"/>have a work from God to do which muſt be their meat, they muſt conſider, that <hi>all things ought to be done decently and in order</hi> in the Church of God; and that they muſt not do things to pleaſe their fancies, or the common ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but our God, and Chriſt our Redeemer, who did ſeek onely the glory of his Father that ſent him; the nurſes of piety and learning, ought to apply their underſtandings for the work that they have to perform, that they may finde ſome means to advance and promote the ſaving knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and keep the Church of God from ſchiſm, licentiouſneſs and hereſie; all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters have a work from God which they muſt accompliſh, <hi>for we are embaſſadours for Chriſt, who hath given unto us the miniſtery of reconciliation,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.18. which is a work of a ſublime excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, where we feed our ſelves with divine meat, when we give others the ſincere milk of the word of God.</p>
                     <p>But further you know, that all Chriſtians have a work from God to do, for they are ſent from him to ſeek after the meat of obedience unto the word of God; that they may live ſoberly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly before him, and by a Chriſtian converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, inflame the hearts of others to the glory of his holy Name: Laſtly, all men and women have their work from God to accompliſh in their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and family as well the greateſt and richeſt, as the leaſt and pooreſt of all; as well the Nobility
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:61843:83"/>as others their inferiours: for to all the intelligent but mortal creatures the time is precious and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for a pious exerciſe, it muſt not be employed about drunkenneſs but ſoberneſs, not about the profanation of the ſacred Name of God, but its holy celebration; nor about idleneſs but watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: Let us then, brethren, forſake our cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous deſires, let us not run after the impetuons blaſt of this world, the time which we have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for our covetouſneſs, pride and vanity, ought to oblige us to redeem it, and to lay aſide the <hi>ſin which doth ſo eaſily beſet us</hi> in this corrupted world, purſuing <hi>with patience the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and looking unto Jeſus the authour and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>My meat is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work.</hi> Amen.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
